좋습니다.
Cool.
여러분 안녕하세요. CME 295 4강에 오신 것을 환영합니다.
Hello, everyone, and welcome
to lecture 4 of CME 295.
오늘은 10월 17일 금요일입니다.
So today is Friday,
October, the 17,
즉, 중간고사가 일주일 남았다는 뜻입니다.
which means that the
midterm is one week away.
시작하기 전에,
몇 가지 안내를 먼저 하겠습니다.
So before we start,
I'm just going
모두가 내용을 잘 이해할 수 있도록,
몇 가지 운영 관련 사항을 확인하겠습니다.
to go over some logistics
to make sure we're all
여러분 모두 기대할 점을 알고 있을 수 있게요.
aligned on what to expect.
중간고사는 다음 주 같은 시간에 진행됩니다.
So the midterm will take
place next week same time.
원래 1시간 15분이었던 시험 시간이
Instead of an hour
and 15 minutes,
1시간 30분으로 늘어났습니다.
it will be an hour
and 30 minutes.
즉, 이 강의실에서 오후 3시 30분부터 5시까지 치르게 됩니다.
So it's 3:30 to 5:00
in this classroom.
평소와 똑같이 진행됩니다.
Just like business as usual.
시험 범위는
In terms of topics,
the midterm will
지금까지 했던 1, 2, 3강과
be about lectures 1,
2, and 3, which we had,
이번 4강까지 포함됩니다.
and this one,
which is lecture 4.
중간고사에 어떤 문제가 나오는지
간단히 설명드리면,
So just to give you
an overview of what
객관식 문제도 있고,
you can expect in
the midterm, there's
서술형 문제도 일부 나올 예정입니다.
going to be some
multi-choice questions along
하지만 주로 수업에서 다뤘던 내용 중심입니다.
with some free form
questions, but they're mainly
즉, 수업에서 본 내용을 바탕으로 문제가 출제됩니다.
going to be about the things
that we've seen in class.
녹화 강의를 보거나 강의에 참석하고,
So if you watch the recordings,
or attend the lectures,
슬라이드를 살펴보고, 중요한 공식들을 알아두면
and just go through the slides,
and know the important formulas,
충분히 준비가 될 것입니다.
I think you'll be fine.
다음 주까지 궁금한 점이 생길 수 있다는 걸 알고 있습니다.
So I know that you may have
questions until next week,
그래서 오늘 Shervin의 강의가 끝난 뒤에,
so that's why after this
lecture with Shervin,
오피스 아워를 진행할 예정입니다.
we will be holding office hours.
자유롭게 찾아오셔서 질문하셔도 됩니다.
So feel free to come to us
and ask us any questions.
물론 그 외에도 저희는
And of course, we'll
be fully available
이번 주와 다음 주 사이 언제든지
between now and next week.
질문이 있으면
언제든 물어보세요.
So in case you
have any questions,
질문이 있으면 언제든 Ed에 글 남겨 주세요.
feel free to ping us on Ed.
저희가 꼭 답변드리도록 하겠습니다.
And yeah, we'll make
sure to respond.
좋습니다.
Cool.
또 이 수업을 청강하시는 분들도 꽤 계신 걸로 알고 있습니다.
I also know that a number of
you are auditing this class.
혹시 아직도 중간고사에 응시하고 싶은 분이 계시다면,
So in case you're still
interested to take
예를 들어 곧 면접이 있다거나 하는 이유로 필요하다면,
the midterm for
some reason, maybe
저희에게 꼭 말씀해 주시기 바랍니다.
because you have an upcoming
interview, just tell us,
그래야 저희가 시험지를 몇 부 인쇄할지 미리 알 수 있습니다.
so that we can just expect
the number of copies to print.
저희가 시험지는 월요일에 인쇄할 예정입니다.
So we'll be printing
this on Monday.
그래서 주말 동안 중간고사에 응시하고 싶으신 분들은 꼭 알려주세요.
So just let us over the weekend
in case you're interested.
네, 좋습니다.
Cool.
중간고사 관련 안내는 여기까지입니다.
So that's for the midterm.
그리고 두 번째 소식은 기말고사에 관한 것입니다.
And then the second piece
of news is the final.
저희가 기말고사 날짜를 조율한다고 말씀드렸었는데,
So we said that we were
working on the dates.
최종적으로 날짜가 확정됐고, 이전과 변동 없습니다.
So we finally finalized the
dates which did not change.
12월 10일 수요일로 예정되어 있습니다.
So it's Wednesday,
December the 10.
네.
OK.
조금 늦은 시간이긴 한데, 오후 7시부터 8시 30분까지입니다.
So a little bit late,
7:00 PM to 8:30 PM.
이 시간대가 저희가 배정받은 시간입니다.
So it's a slot that we have.
장소는 지금과 다릅니다.
The location is
different from this one.
이번에는 이 강의실에서 진행됩니다.
So it's in this room.
그리고 기말고사는 수업의 두 번째 부분만 다룹니다.
And the final will only
cover the second part
즉, 5강부터 9강까지가 범위입니다.
of the class, which is
basically lectures 5 to 9.
여기까지 질문 있으신가요?
Any questions on this?
네.
Yeah.
아, 네.
Oh, yeah.
좋은 질문입니다.
Good question.
기말고사는 오픈북인가요?
So is it closed notes?
아니요.
Yes.
네.
Yeah.
네, 맞습니다.
Yes.
질문이, 객관식 문제의 형식이 어떻게 되느냐는 거군요.
So the question is, what is the
format of the multiple choice?
아직 시험 문제를 다 작성하진 않았는데요,
So you'll have-- so we did
not finish writing the exam,
대략 이런 식이 될 거예요.
질문이 주어지고,
but it's going to be something
like you have a question
답변 후보가 세 개나 네 개 정도 주어질 겁니다.
and let's say, you have
three, four possible answers
그 중에서 정답을 하나 고르면 됩니다.
and then you just
choose the one that.
네, 그렇게 진행됩니다.
That's correct.
이런 형식입니다.
Something like this.
그리고 서술형 문제도 일부 포함될 예정이에요.
And you'll also
have some free form,
즉, 직접 본인 말로 작성해서 답해야 하는 문제가 있을 겁니다.
like you'll have to just
answer in your own words.
네, 그렇습니다.
Yeah.
감사합니다.
Thanks.
질문이, 시험에 뭐라도 가져갈 수 있느냐는 것이죠?
So the question is, are we
allowed to take anything?
네, 오픈북이 아니라서 불가능합니다.
So it's closed book.
그래서 아무것도 가져갈 수 없습니다.
So no.
네, 맞아요.
Yeah.
아무것도 허용되지 않습니다.
Nothing.
펜만 사용할 수 있습니다.
Just a pen.
네.
Yeah.
계산기도 안 된다는 질문이네요.
Question is no calculator.
계산기는 필요하지 않습니다.
You will not need a calculator.
그리고 치트 시트 관련해서도 말씀드리면,
But speaking of
the cheat sheets,
우리가 이미 언급했는지 잘 기억은 안 나지만,
so I'm not sure if we
mentioned, I think we did,
이번 시험을 위한 치트 시트가 별도로 있습니다.
so there is a cheat
sheet for this one,
이 치트 시트는 시험장에는 가져갈 수 없지만,
which we cannot bring to the
exam but you can use just
공부할 때 참고용으로 웹사이트에 올라가 있습니다.
for your studying
that's on the website.
수업 웹사이트에서 확인할 수 있습니다.
Class website.
Jess가 그 치트 시트를 꼭 확인해보라고 권장합니다.
So Jess recommends
looking at it.
좋아요.
Cool.
이제 모두 명확하게 이해하셨죠?
So super clear for everyone?
아주 좋습니다.
Very cool.
네, 좋아요.
Well, OK.
항상 그렇듯이, 오늘 수업도
As always, we'll be
starting the class
지난 강의에서 배운 내용을 잠깐 복습하면서 시작하겠습니다.
just recapping what we saw
in the previous lecture.
기억하신다면, 저희는 지난 시간에
So if you remember,
we basically studied
새로운 형태의 아키텍처를 배웠습니다.
a new kind of
architecture, which
바로 Mixture of Experts, 즉 전문가 혼합 구조인데요,
was called the mixture
of experts, which is such
입력이 주어졌을 때,
that if you have an
input, what you want
모든 파라미터를 반드시 활성화할 필요는 없습니다.
is to not necessarily
activate all the parameters.
즉, 여러 개의 전문가가 있을 때,
And so you are in a setting
where you have multiple experts,
순전파 과정에서는 그 중 일부만 활성화한다는 것이죠.
and in the forward pass, you
only activate some of them.
이런 방식을 sparse MOE라고 부릅니다.
So that's a sparse MOE.
그리고 dense MOE도 있는데,
You also have the
dense MOE, which
이는 각 전문가의 출력을 게이트의 출력에 따라
basically weights the
outputs as a function
가중합하는 방식입니다.
of the output of the gate.
이런 아키텍처는 LLM에서도 사용되며,
So we saw that this
architecture was used in LLMs,
모델을 효율적으로 확장하기 위해 주로 사용됩니다.
and it was mainly used
to be able to scale
즉, LLM을 비용 부담 없이
this LLMs without
incurring an expensive cost
추론 과정에서 모든 파라미터를
at inference time,
because you don't want
활성화하지 않고도 확장할 수 있도록 한 것입니다.
to activate all the parameters.
두 번째로 다룬 내용은
The second thing
that we saw was just
LLM이란 무엇인지 정의하고, 특히
defining what an LLM
was and in particular,
다음 토큰 예측을 어떻게 할 수 있는지 살펴봤습니다.
how you could decide on what
the next token prediction is.
총 세 가지 방법을 살펴봤는데요.
So we saw three methods.
첫 번째는 greedy decoding 방식으로,
First one was we
called greedy decoding,
항상 확률이 가장 높은 토큰을 선택하는 방법이었습니다.
which was always taking
the highest probable token.
두 번째는 beam search로,
The second method we
saw was beam search,
확률이 가장 높은 K개의 시퀀스를 추적하는 방식입니다.
where we kept track of the
K most probable sequences.
세 번째는 sampling 방식이었습니다.
And then the third
one was sampling.
이 방법은 가장 확률이 높은 토큰만 고르는 것이 아니라,
So we're not doing
the most probable.
가장 확률이 높은 시퀀스를 따로 추적하지 않습니다.
We're not keeping track of the
highest probable sequences.
우리는 다음 토큰을
확률분포에 따라 샘플링합니다.
What we do is we sample
the next token with respect
모델의 출력으로 얻어진 분포를
기준으로 샘플링을 하게 됩니다.
to the distribution
that we get as outputs.
그리고 여기서 조정할 수 있는
하이퍼파라미터가 있다고 말씀드렸는데요,
And then we saw there's
this hyperparameter that's
그게 바로 템퍼러처(temperature)라는 것인데,
called temperature
that allows you
이 하이퍼파라미터를 통해 분포가 얼마나 뾰족할지
또는 평탄할지를 조정할 수 있습니다.
to tweak how spiky you want your
distribution to like versus not.
추론 시 비용을 줄이기 위한
최적화 기법들도 살펴봤죠.
And we also saw some inference
optimization techniques,
실제로는 디코딩 단계에서의
큰 비용을 피하기 위해 사용됩니다.
which are used in
practice to avoid having
즉, 디코딩 시 큰 계산 비용이 들지 않도록 하는 거죠.
a big cost at decoding time.
여기서 모든 기법을 다 언급하지는 않겠지만,
So I'm not going to
just mention everything,
예를 들어 KV 캐시 같은 방법은
but I would say KV
cache, for instance,
굉장히 중요한 기법입니다.
is an important method.
그래서 이런 기법들이 무엇인지
알아두는 것을 추천합니다.
So yeah, just
recommend just knowing
다른 방법들과 함께
기본적으로 알아두면 좋겠습니다.
what it is along
with the other ones.
이제 본격적으로 4번째 강의를 시작하겠습니다.
And with that, we're
going to start lecture 4.
사실 오늘 강의를
정말 기대하고 있었습니다.
And actually, I was really
looking forward to today
1강에서는 셀프 어텐션이 무엇인지,
트랜스포머가 어떤 구조인지 알아봤죠.
because lecture 1, we
saw what self-attention
트랜스포머가 무엇인지도 살펴봤고요.
was, what a transformer was.
2강에서는 사람들이 실제로 사용하는 트릭들과
트랜스포머의 여러 변형을 알아봤습니다.
Second lecture, we
saw some of the tricks
실제로 사용하는 트릭들과
트랜스포머 변형도 다뤘죠.
that people use today and
some of the variations
트랜스포머에서 파생된 여러 구조였죠.
from the transformer.
그리고 지난 강의에서 LLM이
무엇인지 소개했습니다.
We introduced what an
LLM was last lecture.
이번 강의에서는 드디어 LLM이
어떻게 학습되는지 알아보겠습니다.
And this lecture,
we're finally going
오늘은 LLM의 학습 과정에
집중해서 살펴보겠습니다.
to see how these
LLMs are trained.
그래서 오늘은 LLM 학습에
초점을 맞출 예정입니다.
So today, we're going to
focus on LLM training.
먼저 제가 말씀드리고 싶은 것은,
And the first thing
that I'm going to say
여러분이 머신러닝 분야에
몇 년 이상 계셨다면,
is if you've been
in the ML field for,
예를 들어, 2~3년 이상 경험이 있다면,
let's say, more than
a few years now, you
전통적으로 어떤 일이 있었는지
눈치채셨을 수도 있습니다.
may have noticed
that traditionally,
어떤 과제가 주어지면,
그 과제에 맞는 모델을 따로 학습시키는 방식이었죠.
if you had a task,
what you would do
즉, 특정 과제에 맞춰
모델을 따로 학습하는 방식이었습니다.
is train a model
specifically for that task.
예를 들어 10년 전이라고 가정해 보죠.
So let's suppose 10
years ago, let's suppose
만약 스팸을 탐지하는
과제가 있다고 합시다.
we had a task which was
around detecting spam.
그러면 그 스팸 탐지에 맞는 모델을
따로 학습했습니다.
You would train a model
specifically to detect spams.
학습 데이터셋으로 학습하고,
So you would train
on the training set,
검증셋으로 성능을 평가한 뒤
마지막으로 테스트셋으로 확인했습니다.
eval on the validation set,
and then test on the test set.
만약 또 다른 예시로 감정 분석
과제가 있다고 해 봅시다.
If you had another use case,
let's suppose sentiment
그 경우에도 해당 과제에 맞는 모델을
별도로 학습한 겁니다.
extraction, you would train
a model specifically for that
이런 방식이 계속 반복되어 왔죠.
and so on and so forth.
하지만 이런 작업들이
완전히 별개의 것은 아니라는 점을
But one could argue
that these tasks,
지적할 수 있습니다.
they are not
completely disjoint.
이 모든 과제는 결국
텍스트를 이해하는 것과 관련되어 있습니다.
They're all involving just
understanding the text.
그래서 어떤 방법을 찾아서
이런 과제들 간의 지식을
So one could argue
we could find a way
학습 과정에서 얻은 지식을
활용할 수 있지 않을까 생각해 볼 수 있습니다.
to somehow leverage the
knowledge that we acquired
예를 들어 한 과제를 학습하는 동안 얻은 지식을
다른 과제에서도 활용하는 방식입니다.
during training for,
let's say, one task
즉, 한 번 배운 것을 다른 작업에도
재사용하는 거죠.
and reuse that for another task.
이런 방법을 부르는 명칭이 있습니다.
So this method has a name.
꽤 오래 전부터 있었던 개념으로,
It's been around for
some time, and it's
"전이학습(transfer learning)"이라고 부릅니다.
called transfer learning.
전이학습의 목표는
새로운 과제가 있을 때마다
So the goal of
transfer learning is
매번 처음부터 시작하지 않고,
to not always start from
scratch if you have a new task.
사전학습된(pre-trained) 모델에서 출발하는 겁니다.
It's to start with
some pre-trained model,
여기서 사전학습이 정확히 무엇인지
잠시 뒤에 설명하겠습니다.
and we're going to see what
pre-trained is, and then
처음부터 새로 시작하는 대신
사전학습된 모델을 내 과제에 맞게
조금만 튜닝하는 거죠.
tune it for your task instead
of starting from scratch.
이것이 바로
LLM 학습의 기본 패러다임입니다.
Well, it's basically
the paradigm
대규모 언어모델은 이런 방식으로 학습됩니다.
on which LLMs are trained.
즉, 이런 다양한 과제들은 모두
결국 언어를 이해하는 작업이기 때문입니다.
So the idea here is
that all these tasks,
즉, 모두 언어 이해를 필요로 하죠.
they involve
understanding language.
그래서 우리가 하는 일은
우선 사전학습(pre-training)이라는
So what we're going to do is
have what we call a pre-training
단계를 거쳐, 아주 방대한 데이터로
LLM을 먼저 학습시키는 것입니다.
stage, which involves training
your LLM on vast amounts of data
언어나 코드가 무엇인지
이해하도록 학습하는 단계입니다.
to just understand
what language,
그리고 나서 두 번째 단계로, 소위
"튜닝"이라고 부르는 과정이 있습니다.
what code is and then have a
second stage of, quote unquote,
"튜닝"입니다.
"tuning."
이제 이 튜닝이 무엇인지
간단히 살펴보겠습니다.
And we're going to see a
little bit what that tuning is.
두 번째 단계에서는
사전학습된 모델을 가지고
But in that second
stage, we're going
이 모델의 가중치를
특정 작업에 맞게 튜닝하는 방법을 찾습니다.
to take our pre-trained model
and somehow find a way to tune
즉, 가중치를 조정해서
특정 태스크에 적합하게 만드는 것이죠.
the weights to adapt
to a specific task.
예를 들어, 아주 큰 모델을
먼저 사전학습한 다음,
So as an example, here, we
would pre-train a huge model
스팸 탐지와 같은 태스크에
맞게 튜닝할 수 있습니다.
and then suppose
for spam detection.
또는 감정 분석과 같은 다른 태스크에도
마찬가지로 튜닝할 수 있습니다.
We would somehow tune it for
that sentiment extraction, same.
이처럼 각각의 태스크에 맞게
튜닝 과정을 거칩니다.
We would tune it
for that and so on.
이것은 앞서 말한 예시와
같은 맥락입니다.
So this is just to take
the example from before.
즉, 이런 대규모 모델을 얻으려면
처음부터 새로 학습하는 것이 아니라,
And the idea here is in
order to obtain these models,
이미 사전학습된 모델을
기반으로 한다는 점입니다.
we're not going to
start from scratch.
좋습니다.
Cool.
이제 사전학습이 무엇인지
살펴보겠습니다.
So now, we're going to
see what pre-training is.
사전학습은 학습 전체에서
컴퓨팅 자원과 비용 측면에서
So pre-training
is by far the most
가장 많이 소모되는
부분입니다.
expensive both in
terms of compute, cost,
전체 학습 과정에서
가장 비싼 단계라고 할 수 있습니다.
everything part of the training.
이 단계에서는 엄청난 양의 데이터를
활용해서
So what it does is taking
a huge amount of data
LLM이 다음 토큰을
예측하도록 학습합니다.
and training your LLM to
just predict the next token.
여기서 말하는 데이터란,
사실상 우리가 구할 수 있는 모든 것,
And here, by data, what I
mean is basically everything
즉 찾을 수 있는 정보 전체를 의미합니다.
you can find.
예를 들어 영어 텍스트일 수도 있고,
So it can be text in English.
다른 언어의 텍스트가 될 수도 있습니다.
It can be text in
other languages.
심지어 소스코드도 포함되고,
여러 프로그래밍 언어의 코드도 해당합니다.
It can be even code, can be
code in different languages,
사실상 인터넷 상에 존재하는
거의 모든 데이터를 활용할 수 있습니다.
can be basically
the whole internet.
어떤 데이터셋이 사용되는지는
곧 다루겠지만,
We're going to see
some of the data sets
이 개념을 쉽게 생각하면,
모델이 어떤 글이든
that people use for that,
but you can think of this
예측하도록 학습하는 과정이라고
볼 수 있습니다.
as just training your model to
try to predict anything that's
작성된 모든 것을 예측하도록 모델을 학습하는 것입니다.
written.
그리고 앞서 말씀드렸듯이, 이때의 목표는
And as I mentioned,
the objective here
다음 토큰을 예측하는 것입니다.
is to predict the next token.
기억하시겠지만, LLM은 텍스트-투-텍스트 모델이고,
So if you remember, our
LLM is a text-to-text model
대부분의 경우 90% 이상에서 디코더 전용 모델입니다.
and most likely a decoder
only model in more than 90%
대부분 이런 방식이죠.
of the cases.
이 모델은 입력 텍스트를 받아서,
So what it does is it
takes some input text,
항상 다음 토큰을 예측하려고 합니다.
and it tries to always
predict the next token
이렇게 반복적으로 예측을 수행합니다.
in an iterative basis.
이런 학습에 사용하는 데이터셋을 보면,
So in terms of the data
sets that are used,
페이퍼에서 Common Crawl이라는 용어를 자주 접하게 될 겁니다.
you will see the term Common
Crawl a lot on papers.
이 데이터셋은 기본적으로 인터넷에서
It's basically a data
set composed of anything
찾을 수 있는 모든 것을 모은 데이터셋입니다.
you can find on the internet.
아마 매달 30억 페이지 정도를
So I think they have something
like three billion pages
수집한다고 보시면 됩니다.
per month.
웹사이트에 들어가보면 엄청난 아카이브가 있습니다.
So if you go on their website,
they have a huge archive.
이 외에도 다양한 웹사이트들이
So there's a bunch
of other websites
함께 포함되어 있습니다.
as well that you
can find in there.
예를 들어, 위키피디아 문서나 소셜미디어,
So for instance, Wikipedia
articles, any social media
예를 들면 Reddit 같은 것들도 있습니다.
as well, like Reddit.
그리고 이 데이터셋에는 Reddit 대화도 상당히 많이 들어 있습니다.
And there are a lot of Reddit
conversations in those data
정말 많은 Reddit 대화가 포함되어 있죠.
sets.
여러분은 코드도 많이 볼 수 있고,
You have a lot of codes,
and of course, you
관련된 다양한 사이트들도 물론 있습니다.
have a bunch of places for that.
GitHub, Stack Overflow 같은 포럼들에서
You have GitHub, you have Stack
Overflow, all these forums
코드에 대해 이야기하는 데이터도 들어 있습니다.
that talk about codes.
이 모든 데이터가 바로 여러분의 모델이
So all of this is
meant for your model
언어와 코드의 구조를 이해할 수 있도록 하기 위한 것입니다.
to just understand the structure
of the language and code.
그리고 데이터셋의 크기는
And in terms of size, so
it's measured in terms
토큰, 즉 토큰의 개수로 측정합니다.
of tokens, number of tokens.
여기서 꼭 기억해두셨으면 하는 규모가 하나 있습니다.
And one order of magnitude
that I want you to remember
바로 수백억 단위,
is on the order of
hundreds of billions
또는 조 단위, 나아가 수십 조 토큰 수준입니다.
or even trillions or even
tens of trillions of tokens.
예시를 들어보겠습니다.
So I'll give you an example.
GPT-3는 3천억 개의 토큰으로 학습되었습니다.
So GPT-3 was trained
on 300 billion tokens.
그리고 예를 들어, Llama 3 같은 경우는
And for instance,
Llama 3, which was
작년에 공개된 것으로 알고 있는데,
I believe published
last year, was
1조 5천억 개의 토큰으로 학습되었습니다.
trained on 15 trillion tokens.
이처럼 정말 방대한 데이터셋이 필요합니다.
So these are huge data sets.
여기서 더 나아가기 전에, 두 가지 표기법을 소개하겠습니다.
So before we go further, I want
to introduce two notations.
이 중 하나는 지난 강의에서 이미 소개한 적이 있습니다.
And I think one of them I
introduced it last lecture.
이 표기법들을 다루는 이유는,
The reason why I want to talk
to you about these notations
이 개념들이 모델이 얼마나 많은 연산을 필요로 하는지 설명할 때 항상 사용되기 때문입니다.
is they're used everywhere
to talk about how
어떤 모델이 얼마나 많은 연산을 필요로 하는지 이야기할 때 쓰입니다.
much compute some model needs.
첫 번째 표기법은 FLOPs입니다.
So the first notation
is FLOPs, which
이것은 floating operations, 즉 부동 소수점 연산을 의미합니다.
stands for floating operations.
이게 무엇이냐면, 연산량을 나타내는 단위라고 생각하시면 됩니다.
And what it is it's
a unit of compute.
FLOPs 값이 높을수록 더 많은 연산이 필요하다는 뜻입니다.
So the higher the FLOPs, the
more operations are involved.
FLOPs란 기본적으로 부동 소수점 연산의 개수를 의미합니다.
Because by definition,
FLOPs is the number
즉, 소수점을 포함하는 숫자를 다루는 연산의 횟수입니다.
of operations that involve
floating point numbers.
여기서 부동 소수점 숫자는 말 그대로 소수점을 가진 숫자라고 생각하면 됩니다.
So floating point numbers,
you can think of them
즉, 소수점이 있는 숫자라고 보시면 됩니다.
as just numbers
with decimal points.
규모 면에서 보면, 대규모 언어모델을 학습할 때 필요한 연산량은
So in terms of order
of magnitudes, training
10의 25제곱 FLOPs 정도입니다.
an LLM is on the order of
10 to the power of 25 FLOPs.
FLOPs를 계산하는 방법은 일반적으로는 복잡한 식을 사용하지만,
And the way you obtain
FLOPs, so usually, it's
사실 공식 자체는 다소 복잡합니다.
a complicated formula.
하지만 여러분은 이렇게 생각하시면 됩니다.
But in your mind,
you can think of it
데이터 크기, 즉 사용할 토큰 개수에 따라 결정되는 함수라고 볼 수 있습니다.
as something that is a function
of the size of your data,
즉, 학습에 투입할 토큰 수와
so the number of tokens
that you train it on,
모델의 파라미터 개수를 기반으로 연산량이 결정된다고 이해하면 됩니다.
and the number of
parameters of your model.
그래서 이 부분에는
보편적인 공식이 없습니다.
So there's not an
universal formula
왜냐하면 이 값은
아키텍처에 따라서도 달라지기 때문입니다.
because it also is a
function of the architecture.
예를 들어, MOE 기반 LLM은
일부 파트만 활성화되기 때문에
So you can think, for instance,
MOE based LLMs as requiring,
계산량이 더 적다고 볼 수 있습니다.
let's say, less compute
because only some parts are
반면에, dense LLM에 비해
MOE는 일부만 작동합니다.
activated compared to,
let's say, dense LLMs.
그래도 보통
이 개념을 간단히 생각하면
But you can just
think of it as it's
토큰 수와 파라미터 개수의 함수로 보면 됩니다.
a function of the number
of tokens and parameters.
두 값의 곱에 비례한다고 생각하시면 됩니다.
즉, O(토큰 수 × 파라미터 수) 정도입니다.
It's like O of the product
between the two, more or less.
그리고 여기서
두 번째 표기법을 소개하겠습니다.
And then there's
a second notation
이것도 FLOPS라고 부르는데
that I want to introduce,
which is also FLOPS,
아까와는 다릅니다.
but it's different.
여기서 FLOPS는
초당 부동소수점 연산 수를 의미합니다.
So here, FLOPS stands for
floating point operations
즉, 초당 연산 횟수입니다.
per second.
이것은 컴퓨팅 속도를 재는 단위입니다.
So it's a measure
of compute speeds.
즉, 하드웨어가
얼마나 빨리 이런 연산을 할 수 있냐는 겁니다.
So it's basically how
fast can your hardware
이 연산들을 실제로 얼마나 빠르게 처리할 수 있는지죠.
execute these operations.
여기서도 몇 가지 단위 차이가 존재합니다.
And so you also have some
order of magnitudes here.
혹시 여러분이 GPU에 관심이 있다면,
But if you're into,
let's say GPUs,
GPU 설명에서 항상
FLOPS가 표시되는 걸 볼 수 있을 겁니다.
you will see that in
the description of GPUs,
GPU 스펙에서는 항상 FLOPS가 명시되어 있습니다.
they always indicate FLOPS.
이 부분은 곧 예시로 보여드리겠습니다.
And we will see
that in a second.
여기서 FLOPS는 보통
모두 대문자로 씁니다.
But I just want to call out
that FLOPS here is usually
하지만 일부 논문에서는
다르게 표기하는 경우도 있습니다.
all caps, although you may
see some papers that use one
이 두 가지를 혼용하면 혼란스러울 수 있습니다.
for the other,
which is confusing.
그래서 어느 상황에 쓰이는 표현인지
문장 내 맥락을 보고 해석하는 게 좋습니다.
So I'll just recommend just
contextualizing this notation
왜냐하면 실제로 두 용어를
바꿔 쓰는 경우가 있기 때문입니다.
with respect to the sentence
that it is in because sometimes
하지만 이 표현이 일반적으로 쓰이는 방식입니다.
people actually switch the two.
여기까지 따라오셨죠?
But this is the common notation.
좋습니다.
So far, so good?
네.
Cool.
자, 이제 우리는 사전학습 단계가 있다는 것을 알게 되었습니다.
So now, we know that we
have a pre-training step.
그리고 이 단계에는 많은 연산이 필요하다는 것도 알고 있습니다.
We know it involves
a lot of compute.
또한, 아주 많은 데이터가 필요하다는 것도 알고 있습니다.
We know it involves
a lot of data.
우리 모델의 규모도 크다는 점을 알 수 있죠.
We know our model is large.
그래서 연구자들은
모델 크기에 따라 성능이 어떻게 달라지는지 알아보고자 했습니다.
So what people did
was trying to see
모델 크기와 학습 데이터 크기에 따라
성능이 어떻게 변화하는지 확인한 겁니다.
how the performance evolves
as a function of model size
그리고 학습 데이터 크기에 대해서도 실험했습니다.
and training size.
이와 관련해 'Scaling Loss for Neural Language Models'라는 논문이 있습니다.
And there is this one
paper called Scaling Loss
2020년에 발표된 논문인데,
for Neural Language Models
that was published in 2020
여기서는 다양한 실험을 진행했습니다.
that performed a
bunch of experiments
이런 파라미터들을 변화시키면서 연구한 겁니다.
by varying these parameters.
연구 결과를 보면, 연산 자원이 많을수록
And what they found was
the more compute you have,
모델이 다음 토큰을 예측하는 성능이 더 좋아진다는 것을 알 수 있습니다.
the better your model learns
about predicting the next token.
학습 데이터도 마찬가지예요.
Same for data set size.
학습 데이터셋이 클수록
모델의 성능도 더 좋아집니다.
So the bigger your training
set, the better it is,
그리고 모델의 크기가 클수록 성능이 더 좋아집니다.
and the bigger your
model, the better it is.
그래서 실제로 2019년부터 2024년 사이에는
So for some time, I think,
between 2019 and 2024,
점점 더 큰 모델들이 계속 등장했던 겁니다.
you were seeing models that
were larger and larger,
연구자들은 더 크고 복잡한 모델을 만들기 시작했죠.
just people just
building things that
실험 결과에 따르면 모델을 키우면
성능이 계속 향상되기 때문입니다.
were bigger and bigger because
according to these experiments,
즉, 모델 크기를 키울수록
성능이 꾸준히 좋아졌습니다.
the performance was
just getting better.
또 한 가지 흥미로운 점은,
So something else
that they noticed
더 큰 모델이 일반적으로
was bigger models
tend to be more
샘플 효율성이 더 높다고 합니다.
what they call sample efficient.
이 뜻은, 동일한 수의 토큰을 학습했을 때에도
So what that means is for
an equal amount of tokens
더 큰 모델이 더 좋은 성능을 낸다는 의미입니다.
that is processed,
you will have a better
즉, 같은 양의 데이터를 처리해도
작은 모델보다 큰 모델이 더 나은 결과를 보입니다.
performance with a bigger model
compared to a smaller one.
하지만 여기서 한 가지 고민이 생깁니다.
우리는 무한정 연산 자원을 갖고 있지 않습니다.
But then you can wonder, we
don't have unlimited compute.
연산 자원, 즉 컴퓨트는 비용이 많이 듭니다.
Compute is expensive.
제약이나 단점도 많죠.
It has a lot of drawbacks.
즉, 사용 가능한 연산량이 정해져 있고,
So you have a fixed
compute, and people also
사람들은 주어진 연산량 안에서
try to answer the question given
a certain amount of compute,
학습 데이터 크기와 모델 크기를
어떻게 결정해야 하는지 고민합니다.
how can you fix your training
set size and your model size
더 최적화된 방식으로 말이죠.
in a way that's more optimal?
여기서는 모델 크기를 얼마나 크게 할지
결정해야 합니다.
Because here, you need to
decide how big is your model.
그래서 연구팀은 연산량을 정해두고,
So what they did is they
fixed a unit of compute, which
이 곡선들의 색상이 바로 그 연산량을 의미합니다.
is the color of these curves.
그리고 모델 크기를 다르게 하면서
And they tried training
models of different sizes
학습 데이터 크기도
여러 방식으로 바꿔가며 실험했습니다.
with different
training set size.
그 결과, 항상 여기에
일종의 최적점이 존재한다는 걸 발견했습니다.
And what they saw was that there
was always a sweet spot here,
이 최적점은 어떤 관계를 따르는데, 특히
which followed some kind of
relationship, and in particular,
이 표가 그 관계를 정리해서 보여주는 것입니다.
this is a table that
summarizes, quote unquote,
"최적의 파라미터 개수와 학습 데이터 크기"를
요약해서 보여주죠.
"the optimal set of number of
parameters and training set
이걸 가끔 '친칠라 법칙'이라고도 부릅니다.
size," which is sometimes
called the Chinchilla law.
연구팀이 알아낸 건, 만약
And what they realized was if
you have an amount of training
모델 크기의 약 20배 정도 되는
대용량 학습 데이터를 사용한다면,
set size that's about
20 times the model size,
연산 자원을
가장 '합리적으로' 쓴다는 점입니다.
then you're spending your
compute in a, quote unquote,
즉, 이 방식이 "최적"이라는 것이죠.
"an optimal way."
예를 들어, GPT-3의 경우를 보면
And in particular,
GPT-3, for instance, I
파라미터가 약 1,750억 개였던 걸로 기억하고,
think it was like 175
billion parameters,
정확하다면, 학습에 사용된 데이터는
if I remember
correctly, but it's only
3,000억 개의 토큰 정도였습니다.
trained on 300 billion tokens.
따라서 이 모델은
이 기준으로 보면
So this one, for instance,
is, according to this,
상당히 '과소학습'되었다고 볼 수 있습니다.
"really undertrained,"
quote unquote.
질문이 있었던 것 같네요.
I think there was a question.
네.
Yeah.
[오디오 없음]
[AUDIO OUT]
네, 맞아요.
So yeah.
질문은, 이런 방식이 신경망 구조에
맞는가에 관한 것이었습니다.
The question is, do they
fit the neural architecture?
이제는 모두가
동의한다고 생각합니다.
So I think by now,
everyone agrees
이제 LLM은 트랜스포머 기반의 디코더 전용 모델이라는 점에 대해
모두 동의하는 분위기인 것 같습니다.
that LLMs are transformer-based
decoder only models.
그래서 모두가 같은 모델 구조를 사용하고 있습니다.
So everyone uses the same model.
제가 여기서 LLM이라고 말하면,
So you can assume that
when I say LLM here,
기본적으로 디코더 전용 트랜스포머 기반 모델을 의미한다고 생각하시면 됩니다.
it basically means decoder
only transformer-based models.
[음성 없음]
[AUDIO OUT]
네.
Yeah.
질문은, 아키텍처 변화가 큰 역할을 하지는 않는다는 것이었습니다.
Question is architecture change
does not play a big role.
사실 그들이 그 논문에서 그렇게 말하고 있습니다.
So that's what they say
actually in their paper.
가장 크게 변화하는 것은
They say the thing
that changes the most
학습에 사용하는 토큰의 양과
is the amount of tokens
on which you train
모델의 크기라고 설명합니다.
and the size of your model.
좋습니다.
Cool.
다른 질문 있으신가요?
Any other questions?
네.
Yeah.
[음성 없음]
[AUDIO OUT]
오, 네.
Oh, yeah.
좋은 질문입니다.
Good question.
질문은 모델의 서로 다른 버전 간에
So question is,
is there some kind
트랜스퍼 러닝 같은 것이 가능한가에 대한 내용입니다.
of transfer learning between
different versions of models?
이러한 모델들 중 상당수는 사실상 폐쇄형으로 공개되어 있지 않습니다.
So for a lot of these models,
they're actually closed source.
그래서 이런 내용들이 명확하게 공개되지는 않습니다.
So they don't exactly
reveal these things.
하지만 흥미로운 질문인 것 같긴 한데,
But I guess it's an
interesting question,
제가 일반적으로 답변할 수 있는 내용은 아닙니다.
one that I cannot
answer in a general way.
아마 이 정도가 제가 드릴 수 있는 최선의 답변일 것 같아요.
So maybe I think it's the
best answer I can give you.
하지만 어쨌든 논문들을 살펴보면,
But in any case, when you
look at some of these papers,
해당 모델을 학습하는 데 얼마나 비용이 들었는지를 항상 명시해 놓습니다.
they always state how much
it costs to train this.
그리고 그 비용은 늘 수백만 달러 수준입니다.
And it's always in
the order of millions.
아무리 해도 사전학습은 매우 많은 비용이 드는 단계입니다.
It's always an expensive
step regardless.
좋습니다.
Cool.
이런 맥락에서 사전학습에 대해 말씀드리면,
Just speaking of
that, so pre-training
사전학습에는 여러 가지 어려움이 있습니다.
has a lot of challenges.
그 중 하나가 바로 비용 문제입니다.
One of them is cost.
제가 수백만 달러라고 말했지만, 이건 최소 수준입니다.
So when I say, millions
of dollars, it's minimum.
실제로는 수천만 달러가 들기도 하고,
I think it can even cost
tens of millions of dollars
경우에 따라서는 수억 달러가 드는 경우도 있습니다.
or sometimes hundreds
of millions of dollars.
엄청난 시간과 인력이 필요하고,
It takes a lot of
time, and people
환경에 미치는 영향도 점점 더 신경을 쓰게 됐습니다.
have been mindful of the
impact on the environment.
그래서 최근에는 생태학적 비용도 함께 언급하고 있습니다.
So they've also been including
the ecological costs.
또 다른 어려움은 사전학습 단계에서
So the other challenge is
that the pre-training step
사용하는 데이터가 학습 시점까지의 데이터라는 점입니다.
is on data that is up to the
time at which you pre-train
즉, 모델을 학습시킬 때까지의 데이터죠.
your model on.
이 말은 즉슨,
So what that means is that
the knowledge that you acquire
이 데이터셋으로 학습해서 얻은 지식은
from training on this
data set can only
데이터셋을 끊은 시점까지만 반영된다는 의미입니다.
go up until the date at
which you cut your data set.
이 시점을 흔히 knowledge cutoff date, 즉 지식 컷오프 날짜라고 부릅니다.
So this date is called
the knowledge cutoff date.
결국 이렇게 되면, 여러분의 베이스 모델,
And so what that means
is your base model,
즉, 사전학습된 베이스 모델은
your pre-trained
base model has no way
이 날짜 이후에 생긴 지식을 자체적으로 알 방법이 없습니다.
to know by itself knowledge
that occurred after this date.
이와 관련해서 많은 논문들이
And speaking of that,
a lot of papers,
지식을 수정하거나 삽입하려는 시도를 해왔습니다.
they have tried to edit
knowledge, inject knowledge.
하지만 이건 쉽지 않은데,
It's always tricky because
there's not a clean way
가중치를 깔끔하게 바꾸는 방법이
to change the
weights in a way that
있지 않기 때문입니다. 일부 영역에서는 오히려 성능이 떨어질 수 있습니다.
does not penalize some parts.
즉, 사람들이 원하는 건 지식을 추가하면서도
So I guess what
people want to do
다른 영역의 성능이 떨어지지 않는 방식이지만,
is inject knowledge but not
regress in some other domains.
이게 정말 어려운 문제입니다.
And this is a very hard problem.
그리고 당연히, 이 모델들은
And of course,
these models, they
다음 토큰을 예측하는 식으로 동작하게 됩니다.
try to predict the next token.
여기서 실제로 어떤 문제가 생기냐면,
And there's this
question of what
단순히 학습 때 봤던 내용을 출력하는 경우가 있다는 점입니다.
if it just generates
something that it
학습 과정에서 봤던 내용을 그냥 그대로 생성한다면 어떻게 될까요?
has seen at training time?
이런 경우를 표절이라고 합니다.
So what we call plagiarism.
그래서 항상 이런 위험이 존재합니다.
So there's always a risk.
이런 점들이 바로 제가
knowledge cutoff date를 언급할 때 함께 고려해야 할 도전 과제들입니다.
So these are all the
challenges I just
이처럼 knowledge cutoff date를 이야기할 때
이런 다양한 이슈들이 함께 있다는 점을 보여드리고 싶었습니다.
want to illustrate when I
said knowledge cutoff date.
예를 들어, 여러분이 OpenAI나 Google 같은 곳의 웹사이트에 들어가서
So if you go on, let's say,
the OpenAI website or Google
모델 카드를 보면 항상 이런 정보가 있습니다.
website to look at the model
cards, you will always see--
여기서 잘 보일지 모르겠지만,
so I'm not sure as
you can see from here,
항상 knowledge cutoff date에 대한 안내가 나와 있습니다.
but there is always a line on
knowledge cutoff date, which
이 날짜는 이 모델의 사전학습이 언제 끝났는지를 알려줍니다.
tells you on when the
pre-training of this model
여기서 사전학습이 완료된 시점을 알 수 있습니다.
was done.
예를 들어, GPT-5는 몇 주 전에 공개되었는데
So here, for instance, GPT-5
was released a few weeks ago,
여기에는 knowledge cutoff date가 9월 30일로 표시되어 있습니다.
and here, it says, the knowledge
cutoff date is September 30.
즉, 이 시점에 맞춰 사전학습을 진행했음을 알 수 있습니다.
So you can guess that they've
done their pre-training
대략 그 시점에 사전학습이 이루어진 겁니다.
around that stage.
좋습니다.
Cool.
첫 번째 파트에 대해 궁금한 점 있나요?
Any questions on the first part?
다 괜찮으신가요?
All good?
완벽합니다.
Perfect.
이렇게 첫 번째 파트에서는
So in this first
part, we've seen
LLM 학습 과정에서 사전학습이 얼마나 중요한 단계인지 다루었고,
that pre-training was a crucial
step of the LLM training
이 부분을 살펴봤습니다.
process.
그리고 정말 큰 숫자들이 등장한다는 것도 확인했습니다.
And we've seen all
these big numbers.
그렇다면 질문이 생길 수 있습니다.
과연 이렇게 거대한 모델을
And one could wonder, well, how
can you train such a big model
이렇게 방대한 데이터로 어떻게 학습시킬 수 있을까요?
on such a big amount of data?
사람들은 실제로 어떻게 이걸 해낼까요?
How do people do that?
바로 이것이 이제 여기서 다룰 내용입니다.
So this is what we're
going to see here.
아까도 잠깐 언급했지만,
So this is what I mentioned.
LLM은 디코더만 사용하는
So LLMs, you can think
of them as decoder only
트랜스포머 기반 모델로 볼 수 있습니다.
transformer-based models.
모델을 학습시키려면 이런 것들이 필요합니다.
So in order to train your
model, you need that.
많은 데이터가 필요하고, 그리고
You need a lot of
data, but then if you
아키텍처를 살펴보면 대부분의 연산이
look at your architecture, you
see that a lot of the operations
행렬 곱셈으로 이루어져 있다는 것을 알 수 있습니다.
involve matrix multiplications.
여기서 여러분께 질문을 하나 드리겠습니다.
And I guess I have
a question for you.
어떤 종류의 하드웨어가
What is the kind
of hardware that
행렬 곱셈을 가장 잘 처리할까요?
loves matrix multiplications?
정답은 GPU입니다.
GPUs.
맞습니다.
Yes.
그래서 GPU도 필요하죠.
So you also need GPUs.
사실은 한 대가 아니라 여러 대가 필요합니다.
Actually more than one.
맞아요.
Yeah.
질문 있으셨죠.
You had a question.
[음성 없음]
[AUDIO OUT]
아, 네.
Oh.
질문은 추론용 GPT에 관한 것이었습니다.
Question is GPT for inference.
이 부분에서는 학습에 초점을 맞춰서 설명하겠습니다.
So this one, we're going
to focus on training,
GPU 요구사항은
학습과 추론에서 조금 다릅니다.
but requirements for GPUs,
they differ a little bit
학습과 추론에서 약간 다르지만,
between training and
inference, but in this part,
여기서는 오직 학습에만 집중하겠습니다.
we're solely
focused on training.
GPU 이야기로 돌아오면, 사실 GPU만 쓰는 것은 아닙니다.
And speaking of GPUs, I guess,
it's not GPUs everywhere
예를 들어 Google은
직접 개발한 하드웨어인 TPU를 사용합니다.
because, for instance,
Google, they've
TPU라고 부르는 자체 하드웨어를 개발해서 쓰고 있습니다.
developed their own
hardware that's called TPUs,
하지만 Google 기반이 아닌
대부분의 모델들은
but any non Google-based
models, they've most likely
대부분 GPU로 학습됐다고 볼 수 있습니다.
been trained on GPUs.
좋습니다.
Cool.
그럼 실제로 모델을 학습시키려면 어떻게 해야 할까요?
So in order to train your
model, what do you do?
우선 여러분이 가지고 있는 LLM이 있다고 가정해봅시다.
So first of all,
you have your LLM
즉, 이 모델이 있는데
which is now-- so
it is this model,
여기서는 간단히 설명하기 위해 박스로 표현했습니다.
but now, we're representing
with a box just for simplicity.
먼저 모델을 초기화합니다.
You initialize it.
이 모델은 파라미터가 매우 많습니다.
It's a lot of parameters.
파라미터 수는 대략 수십억에서
So you can think of the scale as
being somewhere around billions
수백억 규모에 이르기 때문에, 굉장히 대형 모델입니다.
to hundreds of billions of
parameters, so huge model.
그럼 모델을 학습할 때 필요한 절차는 무엇일까요?
And what are the steps
involved to train a model?
결국 우리가 하려는 건, 모델의 가중치를 조정해서
Well, what you're trying to
do is to tune the weights,
다음 토큰을 생성하는 방법을 모델이 학습하도록 하는 것입니다.
so that the model can learn
how to generate the next token.
먼저 'forward pass'라는 단계가 있습니다.
So you have one step called
the forward pass, where
여기서 여러 데이터 샘플을
you have a bunch of
data that you're trying
신경망에 입력합니다.
to pass through the network.
이때 중요한 점을 짚고 넘어가면,
And while we do
that, I just want
우리가 반드시 메모리에 저장해야 하는 것들이 있습니다.
to call out things that are
important to note that we
바로 그런 정보들입니다.
need to somehow save in memory.
이렇게 forward pass를 수행하면,
So when you do
this forward pass,
'activation'이라는 값이 있는데,
you have something that's called
activations, which are basically
각 레이어 별로 이런 activation 값이 필요하며,
the values at each layer that
are needed in order to compute
이 값들이 손실(loss) 계산에 사용됩니다.
the loss.
손실은 현재 예측이
정답(label)과 얼마나 차이나는지를 알려줍니다.
So the loss tells
you how off you
즉, 손실을 통해 우리가 학습시키고자 하는 레이블과
모델의 출력이 얼마나 다른지 알 수 있습니다.
are compared to the label that
you want to train this on.
그리고 이 과정에서 사용하는 메모리 양은
And so the amount of memory
that you will use here
여러 요소에 따라 결정됩니다.
is dependent on a lot of things.
예를 들어 모델 크기에 따라 activation 수도 달라지고,
It's dependent on the
model size, which impacts
결국 activation 개수에 영향을 줍니다.
the number of activations.
또 학습에 사용하는 배치 크기에도 영향을 받습니다.
It's dependent on how big your
batch of data is for training.
그리고 컨텍스트 길이가 얼마나 긴지도 영향을 미칩니다.
And it's dependent on how
large your context length is,
왜냐하면 여기서 N제곱에 비례하는 복잡도가 있었던 것
because if you remember, here we
have O of N squared complexity
바로 이 self-attention 연산 때문에 그렇습니다.
because of this
self-attention operation,
여기서 N은 시퀀스의 길이를 의미합니다.
where N is the sequence length.
그래서 이처럼 다양한 파라미터들이 전체 과정에 영향을 줍니다.
So you have all these
parameters that come into play.
자, 이제 forward pass가 끝나면,
So once you do the
forward pass, let's
이제 손실 값을 계산한다고 가정해봅시다.
suppose you compute the loss.
레이블과 비교해서 얼마나 차이가 나는지 알 수 있습니다.
You know how off you are
compared to your label.
그 다음 단계는 손실을 줄이기 위해서
Now, the next step
is to somehow tweak
가중치를 조정하는 것입니다.
the weights in a way
that minimizes the loss.
그럼 어떻게 하면 될까요?
So how do you do that?
여기에서 'backwards pass', 즉 역전파라는 과정이 있습니다.
There is this another pass
called backwards pass.
이 과정에서는 손실이 최소화되는 방향을
So what this pass does
is quantify the direction
계산해냅니다.
where the loss is
going to be minimized.
이것을 우리는 '그래디언트', 즉 기울기라고 부릅니다.
It's called the gradient.
손실 함수에 대해 각각의 파라미터별로
You take the gradient
of the loss with respect
그래디언트를 계산합니다.
to each parameter.
또한, 그래디언트는 메모리에 저장되어야 합니다.
Well, gradients, they also need
to be saved somewhere in memory.
그리고 마지막으로 가중치 업데이트 단계가 있습니다.
And then you have finally
the weights update,
이때 손실이 최소가 되는 방향을 알게 되죠.
which is where you know where
the direction at which your loss
바로 그 방향입니다.
is going to be minimized.
이제 그 방향으로 가중치를 업데이트합니다.
So you apply that
update to your weights.
그리고 일반적으로 다양한 옵티마이저를 사용하죠.
And you typically use
optimizers out there.
Adam 옵티마이저 들어본 적 있나요?
Have you heard of
Adam optimizer?
네, 그렇습니다.
Yeah.
Adam 옵티마이저는 기존 방식보다 더 다양한 기능이 들어간
So Adam optimizer is
just a fancy version
고급화된 버전입니다.
that has some additional
quantities, which
여러 값을 추적하는데,
keep track of--
이 값들은 본질적으로 그래디언트의 함수입니다.
which are basically a
function of the gradients.
즉, 1차 모멘트와 2차 모멘트가 있습니다.
So you have the first moment
and the second moment,
이것은 각각 그래디언트와 제곱 그래디언트의 이동평균입니다.
which is basically the moving
average of the gradient
즉, 그래디언트와 그래디언트 제곱의 이동평균이죠.
and the squared gradients.
이렇게 여러 값들, 예를 들어 1차 모멘트,
And all these quantities,
so the first moment,
2차 모멘트 역시 어딘가에 저장되어야 합니다.
the second moment, you also
need to somehow save them
이 값들도 모두 메모리에 기록됩니다.
somewhere in memory.
결국 저장해야 할 정보가 굉장히 많아집니다.
So it's a lot of things to save.
네, 그렇죠.
Well, OK.
자, 중요한 사실 하나 말씀드리면, 메모리는 무한하지 않습니다.
Breaking news, memory
is not unlimited.
메모리에는 한계가 있습니다.
Memory is limited.
그리고 여기 우리가 보고 있는 것은
And so here, what we
have in front of us
GPU의 사양 설명입니다.
is the description of a GPU.
아마 맞을 겁니다.
I think.
네, 그렇습니다.
Yeah.
H100, 정말 성능이 좋은 GPU입니다.
H100, which is a very good GPU.
그리고 그 사양표를 보면
And you will see in
that description,
GPU 메모리에 대한 항목이 있습니다.
there's a line on GPU memory.
즉, GPU 메모리는 GPU 한 대당 사용할 수 있는 메모리 용량입니다.
So GPU memory is your
amount of memory per GPU.
이 GPU는 80GB입니다.
It's 80 gig for this one.
상당히 큰 용량이죠.
It's quite large.
즉, 대략 수십 기가바이트 정도라고 볼 수 있습니다.
So it's in on the order
of tens of gigabytes.
그래서 이런 모든 것들을 80GB 안에 저장해야 하는데,
So you need to store all these
things in 80 gigabytes, which
사실 그리 많은 용량이 아닙니다.
is not a lot.
그렇다면 우리는 무엇을 해야 할까요?
So what are we doing?
여러분은 어떤 방법을 사용하게 될까요?
What will you be doing?
결국 중요한 아이디어는,
So I guess the
idea is to leverage
한 대가 아니라 여러 대의 GPU를 사용해서
not one but several GPUs in
order to somehow distribute
CPU에 걸리는 부하를 여러 곳에 분산시키는 것입니다.
the load across CPUs.
그리고 그걸 위해 몇 가지 방법이 있습니다.
And in order to do that,
you have several methods,
이제 그 방법들을 살펴보겠습니다.
which we will see in a second.
첫 번째로 소개할 방법들은 데이터 병렬 처리,
So the first set of methods
is called data parallelism,
즉, DP라고도 부릅니다.
also known as DP.
이 방법들이 하는 일은
So what this set
of methods does is
여러 GPU에 데이터를 분산해서,
it distributes data across
GPUs, so that this forward
포워드 패스와 백워드 패스를 각각 독립적으로 수행할 수 있도록 하는 것입니다.
pass and backward pass, they
can all be done independently.
여기서 핵심은 데이터를 배치 단위로 장치에 나눠서 분할하는 것입니다.
And so the idea here is to
divide the batch of data
그리고 그렇게 하기 위해서는 물론,
across devices, and then in
order to do that, of course,
그래서 각 디바이스마다 모델의 복사본이 필요합니다.
you need to have a copy
of the model per device.
물론 각 디바이스에는 활성화값을 계산해야 하니까요.
Because of course, you need
to compute the activations.
이런 모든 연산들을 각자 계산해야 합니다.
You need to compute
all these things.
이렇게 하면 배치 크기에 따라 필요한 메모리를 줄일 수 있습니다.
But when you do that, you're are
able to reduce the memory that
즉, 배치 크기에 연관된 메모리 사용을 줄일 수 있습니다.
is linked to the batch size.
이런 방식을 데이터 병렬 처리라고 부릅니다.
So that's called
data parallelism.
네, 맞습니다.
Yes.
질문이 있는데, 그라디언트(gradient) 업데이트는 어떻게 하나요?
Question is how about
the gradient update?
좋은 질문입니다.
Well, it's a great question.
여기처럼 독립적으로 연산을 했을 때는 어떻게 해야 할까요?
So what do you do when you have
independent computations here
이런 경우를 생각해봅시다.
and there?
그라디언트는 단순히 각 연산에서 나온 그라디언트의 평균이 됩니다.
Well, the gradient
is just the average
즉, 각 배치에서 계산된 그라디언트를 평균내면 됩니다.
of the gradients for this thing.
이 과정에서 GPU들 사이에 통신이 필요하게 됩니다.
So you have some communication
in between the GPUs
이 통신을 통해 업데이트에 필요한 그라디언트가 집계됩니다.
that basically aggregates
the gradient for the updates.
여기서 여러분께 질문을 하나 드리겠습니다.
So I have a question for you.
이 방식이 모든 문제에 대한 해답일까요?
Is this the answer
to everything?
이렇게 단순히 스케일만 늘리면,
If we just scale
up like this for,
GPU 수를 많이 늘리면 항상 좋은 결과를 얻을 수 있을까요?
I don't know, a lot of GPUs,
is it great, always great
아니면 단점도 있을까요?
or do we have cons?
네, 맞아요.
Oh, yeah.
좋은 지적입니다.
Great point.
결국 한 GPU에 모델 하나를 꼭 올릴 수 있어야 하죠.
So yeah, you have
to fit one model.
네, 정말 중요한 포인트입니다.
So yeah, this is a great point.
제가 한 가지 더 추가하자면,
So the second point
that I will add
추가적으로 발생하는 비용이 있는데,
is you have an
additional cost, which
이건 바로 통신 비용입니다.
is called communication
cost, because you
서로 다른 GPU들끼리 정보를 교환해야 하기 때문이죠.
need to somehow communicate
between your GPUs
이렇게 해야 어떤 값들을 집계할 수 있습니다.
in order to aggregate
some quantities.
결국 학습 속도는 느려지게 됩니다.
So your training is
going to be slower.
좋은 점도 있습니다.
It's good.
메모리 확장이 가능하죠.
You can scale up the memory.
물론, 한 디바이스에
모델이 적재되어야 합니다.
Of course, you need to
fit a model on a device,
어떻게 하면 이걸 할 수 있는지도
곧 살펴보겠습니다.
and we will see
how we to do that.
하지만 이런 통신 비용이
발생하게 됩니다.
But you will be incurring
those communication costs,
그래서 모든 게 좋은 것만은 아닙니다.
so it's not all great.
이렇게 메모리 문제를 생각해보면
So speaking of the
memory and the fact
최소한 각 디바이스에
모델을 저장해야 하잖아요.
that we want to, I guess,
be able to at least
그래서 보통 각 디바이스마다
모델을 저장합니다.
store a model per device.
그런데 실제로는
중복이 많이 발생한다는 걸 알게 됐어요.
So people have realized
that there's actually
중복 데이터가 굉장히 많죠.
a lot of duplication.
이 중복 정보를 줄이려는
논문도 발표됐습니다.
And there has been
a paper on wanting
이 중복 정보를 삭제해보자는
연구였죠.
to deduplicate this
duplicate information
이 방식을 ZeRO라고 부르는데,
ZeRO redundancy optimization이라는 개념입니다.
and this method is called ZeRO,
ZeRO redundancy optimization.
핵심 아이디어는 각 GPU에서
And the idea is
that on each GPU,
동일한 파라미터와
같은 그라디언트,
you store the same parameters,
you store the same gradients,
그리고 동일한 옵티마이저 상태까지
저장하고 있다는 점입니다.
you store the same
optimizer states.
그래서 여기서 제안된 아이디어는
이런 값들을 샤딩, 즉 나눠서 저장해보자는 겁니다.
So the idea here is how
about we shard, we partition
이런 값들을 여러 GPU에
분산해서 저장하는 거죠.
those quantities across GPUs?
첫 번째 방법은 옵티마이저
상태를 분할하는 것입니다.
So the first variation is around
sharing the optimizer state.
즉, 이 상태값들을 GPU마다 나누어
저장하게 되는 거죠.
So meaning, we partition
those states across the GPUs.
이렇게 하면 메모리 사용량을
크게 줄일 수 있습니다.
So this reduces the
memory by a lot.
또 그라디언트도 나눠서 저장할 수 있고,
We can also partition
the gradients,
파라미터 역시 분할해서 저장할 수 있습니다.
and we can also
partition the parameters.
이렇게 하면 중복 정보가 남지 않습니다.
So here, we have no
redundant information.
모든 것이 그냥 분산되어 저장됩니다.
Things are just partitioned.
하지만 문제는 오히려
통신 비용이 더 늘어난다는 점입니다.
Well, the problem
is you're going
이로 인해 추가적인 통신 비용이
늘어나게 됩니다.
to have even more
communication costs,
그래도 이런 방법 덕분에
각 GPU에 걸리는 메모리 부담을 줄일 수 있습니다.
but at least it allows for
us to decrease the memory
즉, 각 GPU의 메모리 부담을
감소시킬 수 있는 겁니다.
load on each GPU.
이 방식이 바로 ZeRO입니다. ZeRO 1, ZeRO 2, ZeRO 3이 있죠.
So this is ZeRO, so there's
ZeRO 1, ZeRO 2, ZeRO 3.
어떤 방식을 선택할지는,
And I guess the
variation that you
여러분이 학습 시간에 민감한지,
will choose will be a function
of how sensitive you are to,
또 모델 크기가 어느 정도인지
I guess, training time
and how big is your model
그리고 이것이 실제로 문제가 되는지
and whether this will
be an actual problem,
아니면 그냥 모든 걸 저장해도 괜찮은지에 따라 달라집니다.
or are you just fine with
just storing everything?
여기까지가 한 종류의 방법입니다.
So that's one set of methods.
이런 계열의 방법들은 다시 말해 데이터 병렬화(data parallelism)라고 할 수 있습니다.
So this set of methods is,
again, data parallelism.
즉, 서로 독립적인 데이터 셋을
So it's basically you having
independent sets of data that
각각 다른 GPU가 처리하는 방식이죠.
are handled by different GPUs.
또 다른 방법들도 있습니다.
Well, you have another
set of methods that's
이건 바로 모델 병렬화(model parallelism)라고 부르는 방식입니다.
called model parallelism.
모델 병렬화는 한 배치 내에서의 연산 자체를 병렬화하는 걸 목표로 합니다.
So model parallelism tries to
parallelize the operation even
한 배치 안에서 말이죠.
within one batch.
이 방식에도 여러 기법들이 있습니다.
So there's a bunch of methods.
너무 백과사전처럼 나열하고 싶진 않은데요.
I don't want to sound
too like a catalog.
그래서 모든 방법을 하나하나 다루지는 않겠습니다.
So we're not going through
them all but one by one.
하지만 몇 가지 중요한 것들만 짚고 넘어가겠습니다.
But I will just call out a
few that are worth noting.
지난 강의를 기억하신다면, MOE 기반 LLM에 대해 이야기했었죠.
So if you remember last lecture,
we talked about MOE-based LLMs
여러 시퀀스가 서로 다른 expert에게 전달된다는 내용이었습니다.
and how sequences were being
sent to different experts.
이런 방식을 GPU에 분산시키려면
Well, there is a way
to distribute that
이른바 expert 병렬화(expert parallelism) 기법을 사용할 수 있습니다.
across GPUs via this expert
parallelism techniques, which
예를 들어, 한 expert를 한 디바이스에, 또 다른 expert를 다른 디바이스에 두는 식이죠.
is having, let's say, one
expert on a device, another one
이렇게 디바이스를 나눌 수 있습니다.
on another device.
이 점이 중요한 부분 중 하나입니다.
So that's one
thing worth noting.
또 하나는 텐서 병렬화(tensor parallelism)입니다.
Another one, I will say,
so a tensor parallelism
큰 행렬 곱셈 연산을
어떻게 분할할 수 있는지에 관한 거죠.
is when you have big matrix
multiplications to somehow cut
이렇게 하면 해당 연산에 필요한 메모리를 줄일 수 있습니다.
that in a way that decreases
the memory required for that.
그리고 마지막으로 파이프라인 병렬화(pipeline parallelism)가 있습니다.
And maybe the last one I will
say is pipeline parallelism.
forward pass를 여러 부분으로 나누는 방식이죠.
It's when you consider
a forward pass
여러 레이어로 이루어진
포워드 패스를 생각할 수 있습니다.
as involving several layers.
예를 들어, 한 GPU는
1번부터 3번 레이어까지만 담당하고
So you're going to say that
one GPU is going to only
다른 GPU는 4, 5, 6번 레이어를
담당하게 할 수 있습니다.
be responsible for, let's
say, layers 1 to 3 and then
이런 식으로 각기 다른 GPU가
다른 레이어를 처리하는 거죠.
another one layer 3--
다시 말해, 4, 5, 6번 레이어,
이런 식으로 나눌 수 있습니다.
sorry, 4 to 5, 4, 5, 6,
and so on and so forth.
그래서 이런 형태의
병렬 처리 기법도 있습니다.
So you also have that
kind of parallelism.
이처럼 다양한 병렬화 기법들이
존재합니다.
But anyways, there's
a bunch of techniques.
제가 방금 언급한 것들은
And the ones that
I mentioned they
모델 병렬화 범주에
속하는 방법입니다.
fall in the bucket
of model parallelism.
이해되시나요?
Make sense?
여기 내용의 세부적인 부분까지
알 필요는 없습니다.
No need to know the
details on there.
여러 가지 방법이 있다는 것과
대략적인 개념만 알고 있으면 됩니다.
But I think just knowing that
there are several methods
이런 점만 알아두어도
충분하다고 생각합니다.
and just a rough idea, I think,
is a good thing to have in mind.
좋습니다.
Cool.
자, 이제까지 뭘 살펴봤을까요?
So what did we do?
학습 과정에서 많은 정보를
메모리에 저장해야 한다는 점을 알게 됐고,
So we realized that during
the training process,
이러한 메모리 사용을 줄이기 위한
여러 기법을 살펴봤습니다.
we had to save a lot
of things in memory.
즉, 각각의 GPU별로
메모리 부담을 줄이는 방법이었죠.
So what we saw was
techniques that
이런 기법들은 GPU마다
메모리 부담을 분산시키는 데 목적이 있습니다.
reduce the burden of
having memory per GPU,
그래서 메모리 분산을 위해
이런 방법들을 적용하는 겁니다.
so we are trying to
distribute that across GPUs.
우선 데이터 병렬화와
추가로 ZeRO 기법도 살펴봤고,
So we saw data
parallelism and then
ZeRO는 추가 최적화 기능이 있는
방법이었습니다.
the ZeRO method that has
some extra optimizations.
그리고 모델 병렬화 기법도
함께 알아봤습니다.
And we saw model
parallelism as well.
이제 GPU의 구조를
효과적으로 활용하는 또 다른 기법을 살펴보겠습니다.
So now, we're going to see
another technique that leverages
이 기법은 GPU의 구조적 특성을
잘 이용합니다.
the structure of the GPU.
여러분도 아마 들어보셨을 수 있는데요.
And you may have heard
of this technique.
이 기법을 플래시 어텐션이라고 부릅니다.
It's called flash attention.
실제로 이 플래시 어텐션은
2022년에 Stanford에서 개발됐습니다.
It was actually developed
here at Stanford in 2022.
이 기법을 설명하기 위해서
GPU가 어떻게 구성되어 있는지 먼저 설명드리려 합니다.
And in order for me to talk
to you about this technique,
GPU가 어떤 요소들로 이루어져 있는지
조금 더 이야기해보겠습니다.
I want to tell you more about
what the GPU is composed of.
자, 내부를 살펴보면—
So if you look under the hood--
GPU는 사실 굉장히 복잡하고, 저도 완전히 다 알지는 못합니다.
well, GPU is very complicated
and I'm for sure not--
저 역시 모든 걸 알고 있는 건 아닙니다.
I don't know everything either.
제가 아는 것은 GPU에는 두 종류의 메모리가 있다는 점입니다.
But what I know is that we have
two kinds of memories in GPU.
하나는 용량이 크지만 상대적으로 느린 메모리입니다.
So you have one kind of memory
that's big but relatively slow.
이것이 바로 HBM입니다.
That's in the HBM.
그리고 또 다른 종류의 메모리는 훨씬 더 빠르지만,
And then another kind of
memory that is fast but much,
용량이 훨씬 더 적고, 연산이 일어나는 곳과 가까운 칩 위에 위치해 있습니다.
much smaller, which is
on chip next to where
바로 계산이 진행되는 그 옆에 있습니다.
the compute happens.
이것이 바로 SRAM입니다.
That's called the SRAM.
즉, HBM과 SRAM이라는 두 가지 메모리가 있는 거죠.
So you have HBM and SRAM.
HBM은 대략 수십 기가바이트 용량을 가지고 있습니다.
HBM has something around
tens of gigabytes.
GPU의 메모리 설명에서 보셨던 바로 그 부분이 HBM입니다.
So it's like the GPU memory
that you saw in the description.
SRAM은 훨씬 작습니다.
SRAM is much smaller.
SRAM은 대략 수십 메가바이트 정도의 용량이라고 볼 수 있습니다.
It's like something around
several tens of megabytes
대략 그 정도라고 생각하시면 됩니다.
let's say.
SRAM은 훨씬 더 작지만, 속도는 10배 정도 빠릅니다.
So it's much smaller, but
then it is 10 times faster.
HBM의 대역폭은 초당 수 테라바이트 정도라고 할 수 있습니다.
So this one is a few terabytes
per second let's say.
반면에 SRAM은 초당 수십 테라바이트의 대역폭을 가집니다.
And the SRAM is tens of
terabytes per second.
즉, 두 메모리 간에 속도 차이가 상당히 큽니다.
So it's a noticeable
difference in speed.
그래서 우리는 이 두 가지 메모리의 강점을 잘 활용해서
So what we want is
to somehow leverage
어텐션 연산을 더 빠르게 처리하고 싶습니다.
the strength of these
kinds of memories
이렇게 해서 어텐션 계산을 정확하게 빠르게 만들고자 하는 거죠.
in order to speed
up the attention
여기서 '정확하게'를 강조합니다.
computation in an exact way.
여기서 '정확하게'란 무슨 의미일까요?
So what do I mean by exact way?
즉, 우리는 계산 결과에 대해 어떤 근사도 사용하지 않는다는 뜻입니다.
So what I mean is we're not
making any approximations
계산 자체를 근사하지 않는다는 의미입니다.
to the computation.
우리는 단순히 이 부품들의 장점을 이용해서,
What we're doing is
we're just leveraging
계산이 더 효율적으로 이뤄지도록 데이터를 잘 전달하는 것입니다.
the strength of these components
and sending the computation
즉, 계산 자체를 똑똑하게 분배해서 처리하는 거죠.
in a clever way.
자, 기억하시겠지만 셀프 어텐션 계산은
So if you remember, the
self-attention computation
아주 중요한 이 수식으로 이루어집니다.
is done with this very
important formula.
쿼리와 키에 소프트맥스를 적용하고
So it's softmax of
queries and keys
어떤 스케일링 팩터로 나눈 뒤, 그 결과에 값을 곱해줍니다.
over some scaling
factor times V.
이 방식 덕분에 쿼리가 다른 모든 요소와
So this allows queries to
interact with everyone else.
상호작용할 수 있게 됩니다.
So in matrix form, you
can think of queries
행렬 형태로 생각하면, 쿼리는
as having the number of rows
equal to the sequence length.
행의 개수가 시퀀스 길이와 같고, 열은 쿼리의 차원입니다.
And then columns to being
the dimension of the query.
키와 값도 마찬가지입니다.
And then same for key and value.
즉, 이런 큰 행렬 곱셈 연산이 진행되는 거죠.
So you have this big
matrix multiplications.
이 연산을 표준 방식으로 하면,
So if you do it--
아무런 최적화 없이 계산하게 되는데,
if you do this
computation, the standards
이 경우 우리가 하게 되는 일은
the vanilla way,
what you would do
크지만 느린 메모리, 즉
is store them in the
big but slow memory
GPU의 HBM에 저장하는 것입니다.
component of the GPU.
즉, HBM에 저장한다는 뜻이죠.
So you would store
it in the HBM.
만약 아무 최적화 없이 한다면 이렇게 됩니다.
So here is what you
would do if you were
아무 최적화도 하지 않는다면 이런 방식이죠.
to not do any optimization.
이렇게 크고 느린 HBM에서 행렬을
So you would take those matrices
from the big but slow HBM,
읽어와서 연산을 수행한 뒤, 다시 HBM에 씁니다.
perform the computation, and
then write it back to the HBM.
그리고 다시 그 결과를 HBM에서 읽어와서,
And then you would read that
result again from the HBM,
소프트맥스를 계산한 뒤, 다시 HBM에 저장합니다.
compute the softmax, and then
write it back to the HBM.
그리고 다시 이 결과와 값 행렬을 불러와서
And then you would again load
this plus the value matrix,
곱하고, 또 HBM에 쓰는 과정을 반복합니다.
multiply them, and then
write them to the HBM.
보시다시피 HBM에서 읽고 쓰는 작업이 매우 많습니다.
See, there's a lot read
and write to the HBM.
이처럼 많은 데이터 이동이 일어나고,
So it's a lot of data
transfer, which actually
결국 이 부분이 병목이 됩니다.
becomes the bottleneck.
GPU 자체는 굉장히 빠르지만, 대부분의 시간은
So a GPU is very, very fast,
but then you spend a lot of time
행렬을 메모리에서 불러오는 데 소요됩니다.
just loading your
matrices from the memory.
이렇게 하는 이유는 바로 이 소프트맥스 연산 때문입니다.
The reason why you do that
is because of this softmax
소프트맥스 연산 때문입니다.
operation.
소프트맥스가 뭘 하는지 기억나시나요?
So do you remember
what a softmax does?
소프트맥스는 값들을 정규화해서,
합이 1이 되도록 만듭니다.
So it normalizes the quantities,
so that they sum to 1.
그리고 이 연산은 행마다 따로 적용됩니다.
But it's row dependent
meaning that each row needs
즉, 각 행의 합이 1이 되도록 합니다.
to sum up to 1.
그래서 먼저 이 계산이 필요합니다.
So in a sense, you need that
computation to happen first
소프트맥스를 적용하기 전에 말이죠.
before you do your softmax.
이렇게만 보면,
If you just look
at it like that,
전체를 먼저 계산해야 할 것처럼 보입니다.
you would think, yeah, you need
to do the whole thing first.
하지만 사실,
Well, it turns
out that you don't
모든 걸 한 번에 처리할 필요는 없습니다.
need to do everything at once.
이게 바로 플래시 어텐션의 핵심 아이디어입니다.
And this is the core idea
behind flash attention.
플래시 어텐션이 하는 일은,
So what flash
attention does is it
읽기와 쓰기의 양을 최소화하는 것입니다.
tries to minimize
the amount of read
HBM에서 읽고 쓰는 양을 줄이고,
and write from and to the HBM
and instead takes small blocks--
작은 블록 단위로 처리하는데, 이걸 타일링이라고 합니다.
and it's called tiling, the
method is called tiling.
작은 블록을 SRAM으로 보내서,
It takes small blocks
that it sends to the SRAM,
그 안에서 끝까지 연산한 뒤
so that it gets
computed from end
다시 HBM으로 보내는 방식입니다.
to end before being
sent back to the HBM.
이해가 되시나요?
Does that make sense?
작은 행렬을 SRAM으로 보내서,
So the idea is let's send
small matrices into the SRAM,
완전히 끝까지 연산하고
so that it does the whole
full end-to-end computation
그 결과만 다시 HBM에 보내는 겁니다.
and just send it
back to the HBM,
이렇게 하면 HBM에서 읽고 쓰는 양을
because we want to
minimize the amount read
최소화할 수 있기 때문입니다.
and write from the HBM.
이제 실제로 어떻게 하는지 설명드리겠습니다.
So here is how you would do it.
소프트맥스 계산 기억나시죠?
So you remember, the
softmax computation
쿼리, 키, 그리고 값을 사용하는 그 연산입니다.
with the query and the
key and then the value.
이제 행렬을 잘라서
Well, what you would do
is to cut your matrices
단계별로 순차적으로 연산하는 겁니다.
and then proceed step by step.
그런데 여기서 하나 재밌는 트릭이 있습니다.
But then there's a
cool trick that I
이 트릭에 대해 설명드리고 싶은데요,
want to talk to
you about, which is
바로, 전체 행렬을 모두 계산할 필요가 없다는 점입니다.
that you don't need to
compute the whole matrix
소프트맥스 내부에서 전체 소프트맥스를 계산하기 위해
inside a softmax in order
to achieve the whole softmax
모든 행렬 연산이 요구되는 건 아니라는 거죠.
computation.
왜냐하면 잘 생각해보면, 예를 들어
Because if you think
about it, let's suppose
전체 행렬이 있고, 그 안에 여러 개의
you have a whole matrix,
and then you have different,
열이나 부분 행렬, 즉 S1부터 SN까지가 있다고 해보죠.
let's say, columns or
submatrices, S1 to SN,
이렇게 큰 행렬에 소프트맥스를 적용하면,
well, softmax of
this huge matrix
각 부분행렬마다 소프트맥스가 적용된 결과와
is equal to this matrix,
where the softmax is taken
동일한 결과가 나온다고 볼 수 있습니다.
with respect to each
of these submatrices
여기서 단지 어떤 스케일링 팩터만 곱해주면 됩니다.
up to some scaling factor.
이게 바로 핵심 트릭입니다.
So this is the core trick.
혹시 확신이 안 든다면,
And if you want to
be convinced of it,
소프트맥스 공식을 한 번 보면,
just look at the
softmax formula,
분자는 어떤 값의 지수승이고, 분모는 어떤 합으로 이루어져 있습니다.
it's exponential of something
over some quantity, which
이 분모는 한 행 전체에서 공유되는 값이죠.
is shared across the row.
그래서 이 스케일링 팩터가 그런 부분을 보정해줍니다.
So this scaling factor will just
fix this with respect to that.
이 점을 염두에 두고, 우리가 할 일은
So with this in
mind, what we will do
행렬을 각 슬라이스별로 나눠서 계산하는 것입니다.
is take each respective
slices of this matrices,
각 슬라이스에 대해 모든 연산을 진행한 뒤,
do the whole computation,
and then populate
출력 행렬의 해당 위치에 값을 저장해주면 됩니다.
the corresponding entry
in the output matrix.
예를 들면, 쿼리의 첫 번째 슬라이스와
So we will do that
between, let's say,
키와 값의 첫 번째 슬라이스에 대해 먼저 연산하고,
the first slice of the
query and the first slice
이렇게 반복해서 각 슬라이스별로 처리합니다.
of the keys and the values.
그리고 마지막 슬라이스까지 같은 방식으로 반복합니다.
And then we will repeat for
the other slice until the end.
그 다음, 다른 쿼리에 대해서도
And then we will repeat
for the other queries
끝까지 동일하게 반복하면 됩니다.
as well until the end.
논문에서 자세히 설명하는 것은,
So what the paper explains
is how this scaling factor
이 스케일링 팩터를 어떻게 계산하는지입니다.
is being computed.
여기 보이는 수식은 제가 슬라이드에 따로 적진 않은 내용인데요,
So this one is some formula
that I did not put on the slide,
이 수식을 외울 필요는 없습니다.
so it's not necessary for
you to memorize the formula.
중요한 건 기본적인 아이디어 자체입니다.
It's just the idea.
그리고 여기서 핵심 아이디어는 바로 이 트릭입니다.
And the idea is
exactly this trick.
이 방법을 적용하면, 결국에는
So once you do that,
you basically end up
HPM에서 한 번만 데이터를 읽어오게 됩니다.
with only one read from the HPM.
그리고 이런 값들은 SRAM에 저장됩니다.
And these [INAUDIBLE] quantities
are stored in the SRAM.
이 값들은 SRAM에서 읽혀지고,
And then they're read
from the SRAM, which
SRAM에서 매우 빠르게 연산한 뒤, 다시 SRAM으로 돌아갑니다.
is very fast, and then computed,
and then back to the SRAM.
마지막에는 결과를 합산하기 위해
And then at the end, in order
to accumulate the results,
다시 HBM으로 보내집니다.
they're being sent
back to the HBM.
헷갈리지 않도록 정리하자면,
So just to make
sure we're clear.
초록색은 SRAM에서 읽어올 때를,
So in green, it's basically
when it's read from SRAM,
파란색은 HBM에서 읽을 때를 의미합니다.
and then in blue,
it's from the HBM.
질문 있으신가요?
You have a question?
네.
Yeah.
[오디오 없음]
[AUDIO OUT]
질문은, 전체 행을 사용하는지 아니면 일부분만 사용하는지에 대한 것이었습니다.
The question is, do you take the
whole row or a portion of it?
일부분만 사용할 수도 있습니다.
So you can take a portion of it.
하지만 이해를 돕기 위해,
But just for
illustrative purposes,
여기에서는 전체를 사용한다고 가정했습니다.
here we take the exclusive.
이것은 어디까지나 설명을 쉽게 하기 위함입니다.
This is just for
illustrative purposes.
여러분의 행렬을 완벽한 그리드라고 생각하시면 됩니다.
You can think of your matrix
as being completely a grid.
그리고 그에 맞게 곱셈을 해주면 됩니다.
And then you just
multiply accordingly.
네, 이것 역시 쉽게 설명하기 위한 예시라고 보시면 됩니다.
But yeah, this is just
for illustrative purposes.
네.
Yeah.
질문은 알파 값과 이런 여러 값들을
So the question is,
are you computing alpha
실시간으로 계산하는지,
and all these
quantities on the fly
아니면 미리 추정해두는지가 궁금하다는 것이었습니다.
or do you have some estimation?
이 모든 값들은 정확하게 계산됩니다.
So all of this is
exact, and they're
그리고 반복적으로 계산이 진행됩니다.
computed in an iterative basis.
작동 방식은 이렇습니다. 출력값을 생성할 때,
So the way it works is when
you populate the output,
계속해서 추가적인 값이 생기게 됩니다.
you will keep on having
some extra quantity that
이 값들이 해당 부분을 보정해줍니다.
will adjust for that.
단순히 잘 동작하는 어떤 수식이라고 생각하시면 됩니다.
Think of it as just
some formula that works.
그래서 논문을 꼭 참고해보시길 권장합니다.
So yeah, I highly recommend
looking at the paper.
그 논문에 해당 부분이 아주 자세히 명시되어 있습니다.
They actually explicit
that quite a lot.
논문 제목은 Flash Attention이고,
So the paper is
Flash Attention, fast
IO 효율성과 메모리 효율을 갖춘 빠르고 정확한 어텐션을 다루는 논문입니다.
and memory efficient exact
attention with IO awareness.
모든 링크는 슬라이드에 포함되어 있습니다.
All of the links
are in the slides.
정확한 수식을 꼭 직접 살펴보시길 추천합니다.
But yeah, I highly
recommend just
확실히 이해하고 싶으신 분들은 논문의 수식을 보면 도움이 될 겁니다.
looking at the exact formula in
case you want to be convinced.
좋아요.
Cool.
전체적인 아이디어는 이해되시죠?
But the idea makes
sense overall?
여기에 대해 질문 있으신가요?
Any questions on this?
좋아요.
Cool.
지금까지 Flash Attention에 대해 설명드렸습니다만,
Well, this was flash
attention, but there's actually
논문에는 또 다른 아이디어도 있습니다.
another idea from the paper.
지금까지가 첫 번째 아이디어였고,
So this was only the
first idea, which
이는 어텐션 연산을 빠르게 만드는 내용이었습니다.
was around making the
attention computation faster.
두 번째 아이디어는, 어텐션 연산이 빨라졌으니
The second idea is given that
the attention computation is
이제 역전파 과정에서 더 똑똑하게 처리해보자는 것입니다.
faster, now let's
try to be smarter
역전파 과정에서는
about the backwards pass,
because when you compute
손실 함수에 대한 파라미터의 그래디언트를 계산할 때
in the backwards
pass, when you compute
체인 룰에 따라 반드시 필요한 일부 활성값이 메모리에 남게 됩니다.
the gradient of the loss
with respect to a parameter,
즉, 역전파 계산을 할 땐 이러한 활성값들을
the chain rule will surface
some activations that you
메모리에 가지고 있어야 하죠.
need to have in memory.
하지만 여기서는 이런 활성값을 매우 빠르게 계산할 수 있기 때문에,
Well, here, given that computing
these activations is very fast,
한 가지 아이디어는 아예 활성값을 저장하지 않는 것입니다.
one idea is to just
not store activations
순방향 패스에서 활성값을 저장하지 않거나,
최소한 모두 저장하지 않는 방법이 있습니다.
from the forward pass or at
least not store everything,
대신에, 역방향 패스에서
but instead in the
backwards pass,
이 활성값들을 다시 계산하는 거죠.
compute these activations again.
이걸 리컴퓨테이션이라고 부릅니다.
So it's called
the recomputation.
즉, 순방향 패스에서는 손실 계산을 위해
활성값을 구하게 되는데,
So when you do the forward
pass, you compute an activation
이때 활성값을 저장해서
다음에 활용하지 않고,
to be able to compute
the loss, but then
그래디언트 업데이트 시에 재사용하기 위해
저장해 두는 대신,
instead of saving it to reuse
it during the gradient update,
그냥 활성값을 버리고,
you will just
discard it and then
역방향 패스에서 다시 활성값을
계산하게 됩니다.
recompute the activation
during the backwards pass
이 매우 빠른 기술을 사용해서요.
with this very fast technique.
이렇게 했을 때 꽤 놀라운 결과가 나옵니다.
And when you do that, it's
actually quite remarkable.
연산량은 더 많아집니다.
So you do more operations.
gigaFLOPs는 FLOPs의 단위 개념이라고 보면 됩니다.
So gigaFLOPs is just
a derivative of FLOPs.
즉, 실제로 수행하는 연산의 숫자를 의미합니다.
So it's the number of
operations you're doing.
flash attention에서는 연산을 더 많이 하게 됩니다.
So with flash attention,
you're doing more operations
왜냐하면 사실상 여러 값을 다시 계산하기 때문이죠.
because you're actually
recomputing things.
그런데 그만큼 HBM에서 읽고 쓰는 횟수는 줄어듭니다.
But then so you also see fewer
read and writes from the HBM.
예를 들어, 기존 방식에선 이 수치가 40.3이었는데,
So here, for instance, it
was 40.3 in the standard way
이제 4점... 거의 10배 가까이 줄어든 겁니다.
and then 4 point-- so it's
like almost a 10x reduction.
그리고 실행 시간도 더 짧아지는 걸 알 수 있습니다.
But then you see that the
runtime is also smaller.
이건 정말 주목할 만한데요,
So this is very remarkable
because usually,
보통 뭔가를 다시 계산하면 메모리는 절약할 수 있지만,
when you recompute things,
you are saving memory
그만큼 실행 시간이 늘어나게 되죠.
but at the expense of runtime.
즉, 시간이 더 오래 걸리는 게 일반적입니다.
You're just taking longer.
그런데 여기서는 단순히 시간이 덜 걸릴 뿐 아니라,
But here, you're not only
taking less amount of time,
메모리까지 절약할 수 있는 겁니다.
you're also saving memory.
즉, 모든 걸 다 얻을 수 있다는 거죠.
So you're basically
having everything.
가장 이상적인 결과라고 볼 수 있습니다.
It's the best of all worlds.
이게 바로 flash attention에서 언급한 부분입니다.
So this is what flash
attention mentioned.
이런 방식의 다른 버전들도 있다는 점을
알 수 있습니다.
So you will see that there
are some other, I guess,
플래시 어텐션에도 여러 변형들이 있습니다.
variants of flash attention.
예를 들어, 플래시 어텐션 2나 플래시 어텐션 3 같은 것들이죠.
So flash attention
2, flash attention 3.
이런 버전들은 주로 기존 방법들을
현재 인프라에 맞게 적용한 것이라고 볼 수 있습니다.
And I would say that these are
more adaptation of these methods
왜냐하면 새로운 GPU가 나올 때마다
to the current infra,
because each new GPU comes
각각 새로운 장단점이 생기기 때문입니다.
with new pros and cons, so
strengths and weaknesses.
그리고 항상 이런 최적화를
더 잘할 수 있는 방법이 존재하죠.
And I guess there's
always a way to make
이런 최적화들은 계속 발전하고 있습니다.
these optimizations better.
그래서 플래시 어텐션은
But yeah, I would say
flash attention is
상당히 널리 쓰이는 트릭이고
매우 좋은 방법이라고 생각합니다.
quite a common trick, and I
think it's a very good thing to.
이해가 되시나요?
So does that make sense?
좋습니다.
Cool.
이걸 긍정으로 받아들이겠습니다.
I'll take that as a yes.
네.
OK.
좋아요.
Cool.
자, 이제 마지막으로…
OK, so last thing--
아니군요, 아직 더 말씀드릴 게 있습니다.
no, we have a few things that
I want to talk to you about.
여러분의 LLM에는 수많은 가중치가 있습니다.
So you have your LLM
with a bunch of weights.
이 가중치들은 모두 부동소수점 값입니다.
These weights are
all floating points.
즉, 소수점 아래에 많은 숫자가 붙어 있는
숫자라고 생각하시면 됩니다.
So you can think of
them as just being
소수점 아래에 여러 자릿수까지 숫자가 있는 거죠.
numbers with a bunch of
numbers after the decimal.
여기서 자연스럽게 나오는 질문이 있습니다.
One natural question
you can ask yourself
정말로 그렇게 높은 정밀도가
필요할까요?
is, do you really need to
know that much precision
즉, 성능을 유지하면서
소수점 이하 자릿수를 꼭 다 알아야 하는지 의문이죠.
after the decimal point to
be able to do a good job?
달리 말하면, 정밀도를 어느 정도 줄여서
I guess put another
way, can you just
메모리를 절약해도 괜찮을지 생각해볼 수 있습니다.
cut your precision in
some way to save on memory
그렇지만 성능은 그대로 유지할 수 있을까요?
but then keep the
same performance?
이게 바로 양자화, 즉 quantization의 기본 아이디어입니다.
So this is the idea
behind quantization.
양자화란 어떤 숫자의 정밀도를
So quantization is the
process of converting
예를 들어, 하나의 포맷에서 다른 포맷으로
the precision of a
number from, let's say,
변환하는 과정을 의미합니다.
one setting to another.
이 개념을 더 잘 이해하려면
In order to better
understand that,
부동소수점이 어떻게 표현되는지 아는 것이 중요합니다.
I think it's important to
know how floating points--
정확히 말하면, 부동소수점 숫자가 어떻게 인코딩되는지 알아야 합니다.
sorry, floating point
numbers, how they are encoded.
실제로는, 이것들은 단순히 비트의 집합입니다.
So in practice, they're
just a bunch of bits.
여기에는 어떤 비트들은, 예를 들어,
And here, you have some bits
that are responsible for,
지수에 해당하는 비트도 있고, 또 다른 비트들은
let's say, the
exponent, some that
맨티사에 해당하는데, 맨티사는 기본적으로
are responsible for the
mantissa, which is basically
숫자의 정밀도를 결정합니다.
how granular your number is.
그리고 부호를 나타내는 비트도 하나 있습니다.
And then one that
is about the sign.
이렇게 여러 가지 방식으로 부동소수점을 표현할 수 있습니다.
So you have a bunch of
representations of floats.
가장 흔한 표현 방식들이 이 표에 나와 있습니다.
So the most common
ones are in this table.
싱글 프리시전, 하프 프리시전 등 다양한 방식이 있고,
So you have so single point
precision, half precision,
플로팅 포인트 64, 브레인 플로트 16 같은 것도 있습니다.
floating point
64, brain float 16
이들은 각각 세 가지 차원에서 정밀도가 다릅니다.
that are each having different
granularities for the three
세 가지 차원이란 부분이죠.
dimensions.
가장 흔히 쓰이는 두 가지 표현 방식을 보면
So if we take the
first two rows, which
실제로 가장 많이 쓰이는 두 가지 방식입니다.
are the two most common
representations that you will
플로팅 포인트 16은 16비트로만 표현됩니다.
see out there, floating point 16
is only represented on 16 bits
32비트와 비교해서 말이죠.
compared to 32.
즉, 이렇게 생각하면 메모리 사용량이 절반이 됩니다.
So it takes basically
half the memory
이런 식으로 생각할 수 있다는 거죠.
if you want to think
about it this way.
하지만 정밀도는 더 떨어지기 때문에, 숫자가 덜 미세하게 표현됩니다.
But then it's less precise,
meaning it's less granular.
그래서 우리가 생각해 볼 수 있는 한 가지 아이디어는,
So I guess one
idea that we could
이렇게 가중치나 숫자의 정밀도를 조금 낮추는 것입니다.
have is to somehow decrease the
granularity of these weights
그리고 이것이 성능에 크게 영향을 미치지 않기를 기대하는 거죠.
and these numbers, hoping that
it will not impact performance
너무 많이 성능이 떨어지지 않는 선에서 말입니다.
too much.
여기서 또 한 가지 언급하고 싶은 것은,
So another thing that
I want to mention
다시 GPU 설명으로 돌아가 볼게요.
is back to that GPU description.
여기에도 연산 속도와 관련된 다양한 정보가 있습니다.
You see that there is also
a bunch of information
연산 속도에 대한 부분이죠.
around the compute speed.
그래서 여기 화면이 잘 보이지 않을 수도 있는데요.
So I'm not sure if you can
see very well on there.
슬라이드에 내용이 잘 보이나요?
Can you see very
well on the slide?
제가 읽어드리겠습니다.
So I'll read it.
연산 속도는 어떤 표현 방식을
사용하느냐에 따라 달라집니다.
The compute speed as a function
of which representation
어떤 표현 방식을 쓰는지에 따라서요.
you're using.
여기서 FP64를 사용하는 경우,
So here, if you're
using FP64, which
이게 숫자를 아주 세밀하게 표현하는 방식인데,
is this super granular way
of representing numbers,
연산 속도가 34 테라FLOPs밖에 안 됩니다.
you only have 34 teraFLOPs
of compute speed.
반면에 FP32처럼 그보다 간단한 방식을 쓰면,
But then if you're
using a, let's say,
연산 속도를 2배로 높일 수 있습니다.
FP32, which is half of it, you
can double your compute speed
이런 식으로 계속 됩니다.
and so on.
여기에는 또 다른 수치들도 나와 있습니다.
You have all these
other numbers as well.
즉, 이렇게 하면 메모리를 절약할 수 있고,
So the idea is you
can save on memory.
연산 속도도 더 빨라질 수 있습니다.
You can also go faster.
이 점을 염두에 두고 마지막으로
한 가지 기법을 더 말씀드리겠습니다.
So with this in
mind, I just want
바로 Shervin에게 넘기기 전에
짚고 넘어가고 싶은 내용입니다.
to touch on one last
technique before giving it
그게 바로 혼합 정밀도 학습(mixed precision training)입니다.
to Shervin, which is
mixed precision training.
혼합 정밀도 학습의 핵심은,
So the idea behind
mixed precision training
다양한 수준의 부동소수점 표현을
적절히 활용하는 것입니다.
is to leverage different
granularities of float
이렇게 하면 성능 저하를 최소화하면서
representations such
that it will not
메모리를 절약하고
연산도 더 빨라집니다.
hurt the performance too much
but allow you to save on memory
더 빠르게 처리할 수 있다는 거죠.
and do things faster.
혼합 정밀도 학습의 아이디어는,
So the idea behind
mixed precision training
모델의 가중치는 고정밀도, 즉 FP32로 유지하면서,
is you have your models or
you have your model, you
가중치를 FP32처럼 높은 정밀도로 보존하고,
keep your weights in
high precision, so FP32,
실제로 연산을 수행할 때는
and all the
operations that you do
순전파와 역전파 과정에서
in the forward
and backward pass,
더 낮은 정밀도로 연산을 합니다.
you're going to do it
in a lower precision.
즉, 여기서는 FP16을 사용하는 거죠.
So in this case, FP16.
하지만 가중치 업데이트는 여전히 FP32로 진행합니다.
But then the weight updates
will be done still in FP32.
그래서 논문 저자들이 이렇게 했을 때,
So the authors of the
paper, when they did that,
결과적으로 깨달은 점은, 성능이
basically what they
realized was the performance
크게 저하되지 않았다는 겁니다.
was not degraded too much.
하지만 메모리 사용량이 많이 줄었고,
But then you had a lot
of savings on memory
연산 속도도 빨라졌습니다.
and then it was running faster.
여기서 궁금해할 수 있겠죠.
왜 가중치는 고정밀로 유지하면서
So now you may wonder, well,
why are you keeping the weights
활성화 값 등은 낮은 정밀도로 처리하는지 말이죠.
at a high precision but not
the activations and so on?
여기에는 약간의 직관을 설명할 수 있습니다.
So I can offer you just
a bit of intuition.
우리가 순전파를 수행할 때마다,
So whenever you
perform a forward pass,
사실 어떤 데이터셋에 대해 연산을 하게 됩니다.
you're performing
that on a set of data.
그런데 이 데이터셋 자체에도 노이즈가 포함되어 있죠.
But that set of data
can be noisy in itself.
즉, 소수점 이하의 모든,
So maybe all the
decimal points after--
소수점 이하에 있는 모든 숫자들이
so all the numbers
after the decimal point
실제로 그리 쓸모 있진 않을 수 있습니다.
may not be as useful.
이 가중치 업데이트는 방향성을 잡아주는 역할로,
So you can think of this update
as being more in which direction
가중치가 좀 더 최적의 상태로 나아가도록
도와준다고 생각할 수 있습니다.
should the weights go
to a more optimal state.
즉, 아주 높은 정밀도가 반드시
So it doesn't require
them to be super precise,
필요한 건 아니지만,
but then it's much more
important to keep your weights,
반면 모델의 가중치는
고정밀로 유지하는 것이 훨씬 더 중요합니다.
so the weights of the model
in high precision in order
그래야 양자화로 인한 오차가 쌓이지 않기 때문입니다.
to not accumulate errors
due to quantization.
이렇게 생각하시면 될 것 같습니다.
That's one way just
think about it.
요약해서 말씀드리면,
But the long story
short is if you
숫자의 정밀도를 줄이면,
reduce the granularity
of some numbers,
많은 이점을 누릴 수 있고,
then you will have
a lot of benefits
성능 면에서도 큰 단점이 발생하지 않습니다.
and not a lot of disadvantages
in terms of the performance.
좋습니다.
Cool.
네.
Yeah.
좋은 질문입니다.
That's a great question.
질문은, 이 기법을 모든 레이어의
가중치에 적용하느냐는 것입니다.
So the question is, do
you apply this technique
아니면 일부에만 적용하냐는 거죠.
to all weights of all layers
or just to some of them?
이 주제에 관한 논문이 정말 많이 나왔습니다.
So there has been a
lot of papers on that.
그리고 답변은, 여러 가지 변형이나 방식이 있다는 것입니다.
And the answer is there
are some variations to it.
그래서 꼭 정해진 정답이 있는 것은 아닙니다.
And so the answer
is not necessarily.
관련해서 참고할 만한 자료들이 몇 개 있습니다.
So I do have some pointers.
원하시면 여러분께 공유해 드릴 수 있습니다.
Happy to share them with you.
하지만 어떤 부분이 다른 부분보다 더 중요할 수도 있습니다.
But some parts may be more
important than others.
이 전략은 조금 추상적인 고수준 아이디어라고 볼 수 있는데요,
So this strategy is a little
bit a high level idea,
설정에 따라 항상 다양한 변형이 존재합니다.
but there are always some
variations from setup to setup.
네, 맞습니다.
Yeah.
그러니까 질문이, 사람들이 Chinchilla 논문에 나온
So is your question that
people rely on the relationship
연산과의 관계를 신뢰하는지에 대한 건가요?
between compute--
아, 연산이 아니라 파라미터와 토큰 간의 관계네요.
and sorry, not compute,
parameters and token
Chinchilla 논문에서 나온 그 관계 말씀이시죠?
from the Chinchilla
paper, but it
하지만 그 관계가 실험 환경에 따라 달라질 수 있다는 거죠?
may be different from
their setup which
이런 변화가 뭔가를 야기할 수 있다는, 그게 질문이신 거죠?
may introduce something-- this
is basically your question?
질문이, 혹시 최적의 정밀도(precision)가 따로 있는지도 궁금하신 건가요?
So the question
is, is there also
정확히 어떤 정밀도가 최적인지에 대한 질문이죠.
an optimal precision to use?
사실, 각자 다양한 방식을 사용하고 있습니다.
So I would say, people
use different things.
모두가 똑같이 따라야 할 정해진 방식이 있는 건 아닙니다.
There's not like a set way
where everyone does something.
하지만 이런 스케일링 법칙, 예를 들어 Chinchilla 법칙 같은 것은
But I would say that these
scaling, like this Chinchilla
일부 저자들이 본인의 모델에서 재현하려고 노력하는 부분입니다.
law, is actually something
that some authors,
실제로, 예를 들어 Llama 3 논문에서는
they try to reproduce
for their own model.
이런 관계를 시도해보는 섹션이 따로 있었습니다.
So actually, for instance,
the Llama 3 paper,
거기서 주어진 자원(컴퓨트)으로
there's a whole
part around trying
어떤 토큰 수와 파라미터 수를 가져가야 하는지
to have some relationship
between given
그 관계를 고민하는 내용이 나옵니다.
a fixed amount of compute, what
is the optimal number of tokens
그리고 자신들만의 설정에 맞는 파라미터 수를 도출하죠.
and then a number of parameters
that is unique to their setup.
실제로 연구자들은 이런 실험을
So what people do is they
do this thing themselves
소규모 학습셋이나 작은 모델로 먼저 해봅니다.
on a small amount of training
set and on smaller models,
그래야 비용을 너무 많이 들이지 않기 때문입니다.
so that it doesn't
cost them too much.
자신들의 환경에서 어떤 관계가 있는지
직접 실험해 보려고 합니다.
They try to see what the
relationship is for their setup,
그리고 그 결과를 바탕으로 외삽하죠.
and then they extrapolate.
제가 알기로 Llama 3도
이런 식으로 진행했습니다.
And I believe
that's how Llama 3--
즉, 이런 방식으로 만든 모델이 있습니다.
so I think there's
a model that--
Llama 3는 파라미터 수가 4050억에 달합니다.
so Llama 3, 405
billion parameters.
이 값이 어떻게 나왔는지 설명하는
섹션이 있던 것으로 기억합니다.
I think they had the whole
section just justifying
실험을 통해 이 수치를 정당화했다고
명시되어 있었습니다.
that they came up to this
number with some experiments
즉, 그런 실험을 직접 했던 거죠.
that they run.
따라서 질문하신 내용에 대해 답을 드리자면,
So to your question,
I think it highly
이건 학습하는 모델의 종류에
상당히 많이 좌우됩니다.
depends on the kind of model
that someone is training.
그래서 아마 각자 자기가 사용하는 환경과 관련하여
이런 분석을 하게 될 겁니다.
And they'll probably
have this analysis,
결국 자기 환경에 따라 다르게 접근한다는 거죠.
I guess, with respect
to their own setup.
이렇게 설명하면 궁금하신 점이 해결되셨나요?
Does that answer your question?
좋아요.
Cool.
좋습니다.
네.
OK.
좋아요.
Great.
네.
Yeah.
이번 질문은, 이 범위와 관련해서
무언가 할 수 있는 게 있는지입니다.
The question is,
is there something
이 범위에 대해 우리가 할 수 있는 게 있을까요?
you can do about the range?
여러 가지 양자화(quantization) 방식이 있습니다.
So there are several
types of quantization.
여기서 자세히 설명하진 않겠지만,
We're not going
into details here,
제로포인트 양자화(ZeRO point quantization)와
absmax 양자화 같은 방법이 있습니다.
but I can give you a ZeRO
point quantization and absmax
이런 방식들은
서로 다른 기법에 속합니다.
quantization, which are
different techniques that
이런 기법들이
값의 범위를 조절하는 데 쓰입니다.
play with these ranges.
여기에는 또 다른 양자화 기법도 있는데,
There's also
quantization technique
Shervin이 이후에 이 내용도 함께 소개할 예정입니다.
that Shervin will cover
that also talks about that.
이 부분은 계속해서 살펴보시면 좋을 것 같아요.
So yeah, stay tuned for this.
ZeRO point quantization과 absmax가
이 경우 참고해볼 만한 기법이라고 생각합니다.
But I think ZeRO point
quantization and absmax are
이 방법들에 대해 추가로 찾아보셔도 좋겠습니다.
ones that maybe you
can look into for this.
좋습니다.
Cool.
이제 그러면, 셰르빈에게 마이크를 넘기겠습니다.
So with that, I'm going
to give it to Shervin.
감사합니다, 아프신.
Thank you, Afshin.
자, 이제 우리는 사전학습이 어떻게 이루어지는지 살펴봤습니다.
So now, we have seen how
a pre-training worked.
이제 이어서 다음 학습 단계들을 함께 살펴보겠습니다.
We're going to see together
the next stages of training.
아프신과 함께 본 것처럼, 사전학습은
So as we saw with
Afshin, pre-training
모델이 언어에 대한 직관을 쌓을 수 있도록 하는 과정이었습니다.
was a way to build the intuition
to the model about how language
언어가 어떻게 만들어지는지와 학습 데이터에
어떤 주요 특성들이 있는지에 대해 알려주는 과정이죠.
was constructed and about the
main characteristics of what is
이런 정보들은 일반적인 지식들입니다.
contained in the training data.
즉, 충분히 일반화된 내용이라는 뜻이죠.
That is general enough.
그래서 우리는 매우 방대한 규모의 말뭉치를 사용하고,
So this is why we had corpuses
that spans huge corpora of texts
보통 그 크기는 인터넷에서 찾을 수 있는
that are typically
of the size of what
자료들과 비슷하게 아주 큽니다.
you find on the internet.
이런 데이터는 보통 아주 크고, 가공되지 않은 형태이며,
So typically, very large
and raw and conveying
언어의 여러 측면을 잘 반영합니다.
aspects of language.
자, 이제 여러분은 이런 지식을
어떻게 실제로 유용하게 쓸 수 있을지 생각해볼 수 있습니다.
So now, you might
want to ask yourself,
이 지식을 어떻게 활용할 수 있을지
이 부분을 이제 곧 이야기하겠습니다.
how can we make such
knowledge actually helpful?
이제 바로 그 내용을 이야기할 텐데요.
So this is something
that we're going
이 주제에 대해 본격적으로 이야기하기 전에,
to discuss just in a second.
왜 추가 학습이 필요한지 동기를 알려줄 수 있는
But before we discuss about what
could motivate further training,
아주 간단한 예시로 다시 한번 돌아가 보려고 합니다.
I want to come back to some very
simple example that will surface
어떤 필요가 있을 수 있는지 보여주는 예시입니다.
what could be such a need.
자, 우리가 자주 들었던 테디베어 예시를 들어볼게요.
So let's take our favorite
example about our teddy bear.
그리고 실제로 활용할 수 있는
아주 실용적인 상황을 생각해 보죠.
And let's say, we have a
very practical use case.
여러분은 테디베어를 정말 아끼고 있었는데,
So we have thoroughly
loved our teddy bear.
이제 이 테디베어가 조금 더러워져서
세탁을 해야 할 상황이 됐다고 해봅시다.
But now, it has become a bit
dirty, so we need to wash it.
그래서 여러분이 좋아하는 LLM에게
이 테디베어를 세탁기에 넣어도 되는지 물어볼 수 있습니다.
And you might want to ask your
favorite LLM if you can put it
세탁기에 넣어도 될지 묻는 거죠.
in the washer.
아프신이 언급한 LLM 사전학습 방식과 연결해서,
So with the description
that Afshin mentioned
이 상황에서 여러분은 어떤 답변이 나올지 한번 생각해보셨으면 합니다.
of LLM pre-training,
I wanted to ask
여러분은 이 경우, 어떤 결과가 나올지 어떻게 생각하시나요?
you all what was your
opinion about what
결과가 어떻게 될 수 있을까요?
could the output to this be.
혹시 추측해볼 분 있나요?
So any guesses?
네.
Yep.
좋아요.
Yeah.
네.
아주 좋습니다.
Excellent.
네.
Yeah.
그래서 방금 답변은 또 다른 질문이 나올 수도 있다는 것이었죠.
So the answer, the guess
was maybe another question.
그건 정말 좋은 추측입니다. 실제로 그럴 수도 있죠.
So I think that is a great guess
that could definitely be it.
이 예시에서는 우리가 다른 문장을 넣었지만,
So here, in the example,
we put some other sentence
핵심은 똑같습니다.
that could be likely,
but the gist is the same.
이 모델은 다음 토큰 예측에 맞춰 학습되었지,
It has been trained on
next token prediction,
여러분을 돕는 어시스턴트로 학습된 건 아닙니다.
not being an assistant or
someone that is helpful to you.
그래서 이런 이유로 모델은 해당 패턴이 무엇인지,
So this is why it
will try to mimic
그리고 여기서 어떤 다음 단어가 나올지
what could be the pattern
here and what could
확률이 높은 다음 단어를 모방하려고 합니다.
be potential likely next words.
예를 들어, 우리가 예시로 넣은 문장도
So for example, the
example we put here
테디베어가 어떻게 만들어졌는지와 관련된 내용입니다.
is something that relates to how
the teddy bear is composed of.
테디베어와 같은 주제이기 때문에
And because it's in the
same domain as teddy bear
여러분이 세탁기에 대해 얘기하면,
and then when you talk
about washer, then
모델이 테디베어의 소재 데이터로 학습되었을 수도 있습니다.
maybe it has been trained
on data that includes
테디베어의 소재와 관련된 내용이죠.
materials of teddy bears.
그래서 그런 결과가 나올 수 있습니다.
So that could be it.
여기서 여러분께 질문이 하나 더 있습니다.
And I have a question
with you all.
여러분은 이 결과에 만족하시나요?
Are you happy with it?
아니요.
No.
네.
Yeah.
맞아요.
Exactly.
이 때문에 이제 우리가
So this is why
we're going to see
모델을 어떻게 활용하면 여러분에게 더 도움이 될 수 있을지 살펴보겠습니다.
what we can do with the model
to make it helpful to you.
이 단계가 바로 파인튜닝이라고 부릅니다.
And this stage is
called fine tuning.
파인튜닝을 하면 어떤 것이 가능해지는지 살펴볼 텐데요,
So we're going to see
that it enables us to,
일반적인 LLM의 경우,
in the general
case of LLMs, make
LLM이 유용한 어시스턴트가 되도록 할 수도 있고,
the LLM a helpful
assistance, but also,
여러분이 특정 용도에 맞춰 쓰고 싶다면,
if you have a
specific use case, you
이런 기법으로 그 부분에 맞게
조정할 수도 있습니다.
can also use this
technique to tune
언어의 일반적 표현을
여러분이 원하는 작업 방향으로
the general representation
of the language
조율할 수 있게 되는 거죠.
towards your task of interest.
먼저, 우리가 초점을 맞출 것은
But we're going to
focus first on what
일반적으로 LLM에서는 무엇을 하는지입니다.
is done for LLMs in general.
먼저, 용어를 간단히 정의하고 넘어가겠습니다.
So first, I want to
define some terms.
모델 파인튜닝은 흔히 SFT라고도 부릅니다.
So model fine tuning is
commonly known as SFT.
SFT는 supervised fine tuning의 약자입니다.
SFT is short for
supervised fine tuning.
supervised라는 말은 레이블이 필요하다는 의미고,
So the supervised part suggests
that we need some labels.
실제로 레이블이 필요합니다.
And it's actually the case.
즉, 입력과 출력 쌍을
So it's pairs of
inputs and outputs
모델에 학습용으로 제공하는 겁니다.
that we provide the
model to be trained on.
그래서 supervised라고 부르는 거죠.
And this is why it's
called supervised.
그리고 파인튜닝이라는 용어는
And then fine tuning
is the term that
이미 학습된 가중치를 좀 더 정교하게 다듬는 것을 의미합니다.
refers to refining the weights
that have been already trained.
즉, 사전학습된 가중치에서 시작해서
So you start from the
pre-trained weights,
추가 데이터를 가지고
모델을 더 학습하는 방식입니다.
and you further train the
model on additional data
이렇게 해서 파인튜닝된 모델을 얻게 됩니다.
to get a fine tuned model.
여기서 흥미로운 점 하나를 말씀드릴게요.
And then one interesting
note that I will tell you all
목적 함수 자체는 같지만,
is that the objective function,
even though it's the same,
사전학습 때 쓰는 과제와는 약간 다를 수 있습니다.
will differ a bit from
the pre-training task.
사전학습에서는 BOS 토큰,
즉 문장 시작 토큰에서 출발해서
So in the pre-training task,
you start with the BOS token,
모든 데이터 코퍼스에 대해
다음 토큰을 예측하게 됩니다.
beginning of
sentence, and you fit
계속해서 다음 토큰을 맞히는 식으로 전체 데이터를 학습합니다.
all your corpora of data trying
to predict the next token.
하지만 여기서는 지도 학습 기반 파인튜닝 환경이기 때문에,
But here, since we have this
supervised fine tuning setup,
모델이 실제로 유용한 작업을 수행하길 원합니다.
where you want the model to
do something useful in cases
예를 들어, 제가 모델에게 어떤 질문을 할 때,
of interest, so let's
say, when I ask the model
'내 곰인형을 세탁하는 방법'처럼요.
about washing my teddy bear,
so washing my teddy bear
이 경우, '내 곰인형을 세탁하는 방법'이라는 입력이 모델에 주어집니다.
is actually an input
that I give to the model.
이 입력은 고정되어 있습니다.
It's fixed.
저는 모델이 제 말을 따라 반복하길 원하지 않습니다.
I don't want the model
to parrot what I say.
모델이 유용한 어시스턴트 역할을 하길 바랍니다.
I want the model to be
a helpful assistance
제가 입력한 내용에 대해 도움을 주는 식으로요.
to what I conditioned it on.
이런 환경에서는,
입력이 바로 다음 토큰을 예측하는 위치가 아닙니다.
So in this setup, the
input is not a location
즉, 그 입력에서 바로 다음 토큰을 예측하는 것은 아니라는 뜻입니다.
where you would
predict the next token.
여기서는 teacher forcing을 적용하지 않고,
You would not do
teacher forcing on it
이 입력에서부터 시작해서,
but rather start from this
input and then predict
그 이후의 토큰을 예측하게 됩니다.
the next token onwards.
그리고 이때부터
어떤 토큰이 최적인지,
And then you're
going to tune what
즉, 다음 토큰의 최적 분포를
the optimal distribution
of next token
이 입력을 바탕으로 조정하게 됩니다.
can be based on this input.
SFT의 전체적인 아이디어에 대해
여기까지 질문 있으신가요?
So any questions on
the overall idea of SFT
조금 더 깊게 들어가기 전에 질문 받겠습니다.
before we dive in a bit deeper?
네.
Yep.
그러니까 질문은 입력 부분에는 손실을 적용하지 않는다는 것이죠.
So the question is we don't
put a loss over the input.
맞습니다.
That's right.
입력에서부터 시작해서,
So you start from the
input, and you start
그 다음 토큰을 예측하기 시작합니다.
predicting the next token.
그리고 손실 계산은 그 지점부터 시작됩니다.
And then the loss calculation
starts from there.
여기까지 괜찮으신가요?
Everything good?
좋습니다.
OK.
지금까지 설명드린 내용을 정리하면,
So what I was just
telling you is
SFT는 여러분이 원하는 특정 과업에 맞게 모델을 파인튜닝하는 데 쓸 수 있고,
that SFT can be done to tune
your own task of interest,
또한, 실제로는
but also, it's
something that is being
그리고 이것은 LLM 학습의 주요 단계 중 하나에서
적용되고 있습니다.
done at one of the main
stages of training LLMs
여러분이 매일 사용하는 과정에서 이뤄집니다.
as you use it every day.
그리고 이제 모델이
And then this transition
from the model
언어를 잘 표현하는 수준에서 실질적인 도움을 주는 단계로
전환되는 과정이 있습니다.
being a good representation of
language to a useful assistance
이 과정은 SFT의 하위 개념인
instruction tuning이라고 부릅니다.
is a subcategory of SFT
called instruction tuning.
instruction tuning이라는 용어는
우리가 모델에게 명령을 잘 따르도록 학습시키고 싶다는 점에서 나왔습니다.
So instruction tuning
comes from the fact
즉, 모델이 주어진 지시에 응답하도록 만드는 것이죠.
that we want the model
to answer instructions.
이제 그래프를 통해
방금 설명했던 개념을 보여드리겠습니다.
So now, I'm going to
show with the graph what
특히 다음 단어 예측과 관련된 부분을
그래프로 설명하겠습니다.
I was just mentioning regarding
predicting the next word.
자, 바로 설명드릴게요.
So actually, just in a bit.
먼저, 데이터를 살펴보겠습니다.
First, we're going
to look at the data.
Afshin과 함께 살펴본 것처럼,
So with Afshin, we saw
that the composition
사전학습용 데이터는 기본적으로
of the data for
pre-training was basically
인터넷 전체에서 수집된 데이터였죠.
위키피디아처럼 지식을 담고 있는 소스들이 있습니다.
the whole internet where you
had sources that were carrying
대표적으로 위키피디아가 있죠.
knowledge such as Wikipedia.
그리고 전반적으로 방대한 텍스트 데이터가 영어뿐만 아니라
And in general, masses
of text of English
영어와 기타 언어가 어떻게 작동하는지
모델에게 알려줍니다.
that tells the model about how
English and other languages
프로그래밍 코드도 포함됩니다.
work, as well as coding.
하지만 instruction tuning에서는
이 부분이 조금 다릅니다.
And here, it's
slightly different.
instruction tuning을 위해서는 모델에게
For instruction
tuning, we're going
어떻게 하면 주어진 지시에 가장 효과적으로
응답할 수 있는지 알려주는 데이터를 사용합니다.
to look at data that's
presents to the model
즉, 모델이 지시에 잘 응답할 수 있도록
도움이 되는 방식으로 데이터를 제공합니다.
how it can most helpfully
respond to instructions.
이 데이터는 여러 가지 유형으로
나눌 수 있습니다.
So you can divide this
in several categories.
여기서는 몇 가지 카테고리를
소개하겠습니다.
So here, we present
some categories
이런 데이터들은 LLM 사용자에게
아주 유용할 수 있습니다.
that could be helpful
to users of LLMs.
예를 들어, 이야기 작성 같은 경우입니다.
For example, story writing.
여러분이 이야기를 쓰고 싶다고 가정해 보겠습니다.
You're interested
in writing a story.
지시 사항들을 주고,
You give it a set
of instructions,
여기에 해당하는 정답 데이터를
같이 제공합니다.
and then you have a ground
truth that is attached to it.
다른 예로는 시 짓기, 목록 생성 등이
포함될 수 있습니다.
Other examples include a poem
creation, list generation,
설명 작성이나 그 외에도
여러 가지 작업이 포함됩니다.
explanation, and many
more that are part
이런 작업들이 SFT 데이터 믹스처의 일부입니다.
of the data mixture of SFT.
즉, 이런 전체 작업들에 대해
감독 학습 기반 파인튜닝을 진행합니다.
So basically, you run all these
supervised fine tuning training
주어진 입력을 바탕으로
모델을 학습시키는 것이죠.
with the inputs that is given,
and then you train the model
출력값을 예측하도록 모델을 훈련합니다.
on predicting the output.
이제 실제로 어떻게 생겼는지 보여드리겠습니다.
And I'm going now to
show what it looks like.
여기에 여러분의 인스트럭션을
넣었다고 해봅시다.
So let's say your
instruction is here.
모델에게 어떤 작업을 하라고 요청하는 거죠.
So you ask your model
to do something.
이 요청은 다양한 형태로 표현될 수 있지만,
So it could be formulated
in a different way
간단히 말해서, 'X를 수행하라'고 써뒀다고 합시다.
but just to keep it
short, I just said, do X.
그리고 노란색 부분이 바로
And then the yellow
part is where
여기서부터 목표 함수를
맞춰나가기 시작하는 구간입니다.
you start fitting your
objective function on.
이해되시나요?
Does this make sense?
좋아요.
Great.
방금 말씀드렸듯이, 데이터 믹스처에는
So as I was mentioning,
the data mixture
인스트럭션 중심의 데이터가 포함되어 있습니다.
includes instruction
geared data.
예를 들면, 이전에 말씀드린 이런 작업들이 있죠.
So for example, you had
all of these kinds of tasks
사용자들이 추론 단계에서
요청할 수 있는 다양한 작업입니다.
that users might ask
for at inference time.
이런 것들을 전부 어시스턴트 대화 데이터로
범주화해서 넣었습니다.
So it's what I put under the
category assistant dialogues.
그리고 요즘은, 이미 다양한 대규모 모델들이
And these days, since you have
all these large models that
기존에 존재하기 때문에,
already exist out
there, and let's say
만약 새로운 모델을 만든다고 해도,
you want to generate a new
one, you don't necessarily
꼭 처음부터 시작할 필요는 없습니다.
have to start from scratch.
제가 언급한 모든 예시는 원래 사람이 쓴 것이었습니다.
So all of these that I mentioned
were originally human written.
즉, 이런 모든 인스트럭션들이 있었고,
So you had all
these instructions
여러 사람들이 모은 데이터와 함께
언어 전문가들이
that people gathered, and
you had expert linguists that
최고의 답변을 쓰는 방법에 대한 인스트럭션을 제공했습니다.
had set of instructions on how
to write the best answer that
이 답변은 자연스럽고, 유용하며,
was fluent, helpful,
and everything
모든 것이 사용자의 만족도를
that was geared
towards maximizing
극대화하는 방향으로 구성되어 있었습니다.
your happiness as a user.
하지만 요즘에는 이미 학습된 LLM을 활용해서
But these days, you can use
these already trained LLMs
이런 데이터를 생성할 수 있습니다.
to generate such data.
보통 아주 성능이 좋은 대규모 모델이 있다면,
So typically, when you
have a large model that
이런 지침을 입력해서 출력 샘플을 생성할 수 있고,
is very performant, you can feed
it such instructions, sample
그 뒤에 사람이거나 또 다른 LLM이
some generated outputs, and then
have a human or some other LLM
출력 품질을 검토하게 됩니다.
review the quality.
이런 식으로 데이터셋을 만들 때
So it's something
that speeds up a bit
속도를 좀 더 낼 수 있게 되는 거죠.
the curation of such data sets.
그리고 한 가지 더 강조하고 싶은 점은,
So I just wanted to
emphasize on the fact
요즘엔 반드시 사람이 직접 데이터를 만들지 않아도
that it's not only human
generated these days,
이런 식으로 도움을 받을 수 있다는 겁니다.
but you can have
some assistance.
그리고 우리가 신경 써야 하는 또 다른 범주로는,
And besides all
of the categories
예를 들면 수학이나 증명 작성,
that you care about,
so typically, math
논리 전개의 타당성, 혹은
or how you write a proof,
how things follow each other,
고품질 코드와 같이 코드 베이스의 품질 등이 있습니다.
or codes, high
quality code bases,
여기에 더해 대중에 공개되는 제품에서는
you also have other aspects
that are very important which
특히 중요한 또 다른 요소들이 존재합니다.
when you release a product like
this to the wider population
이러한 요소들은 전반적으로 안전성 범주에
that come under the
umbrella of safety.
포함된다고 볼 수 있습니다. 여러분의 모델이
So you want your model to be
helpful but also harmless.
유용할 뿐만 아니라 해롭지 않게 하는 것이 중요합니다.
So you also have
in the data mixture
그래서 데이터 구성에는 종종 모델의 행동을
oftentimes a subset that
enforces the model's behavior
규제하기 위한 일부 하위 데이터가 포함됩니다.
not to repeat some of
the harmful content it
이렇게 함으로써 사전학습 데이터에서
might have seen on its
pre-training corpus.
얻었을지도 모를 유해한 내용을 모델이
So it will include
techniques that
반복하지 않도록 하는 기법들이 들어갑니다.
might reject some user prompts.
여러분도 직접 LLM의 한계가 어디까지인지
So you might have tested on your
own the limits of an LLM today.
테스트해 보신 분이 계실 텐데요, 만약 부적절하다고
If you submit queries that
might lead to something that is
여겨지는 쿼리를 입력하면 모델이 '죄송합니다.'라며
considered bad, it would
just say, OK, sorry,
답변을 거부하는 경우가 있습니다.
I cannot answer this.
이런 '죄송합니다, 답변할 수 없습니다.'는 간단히 regex로 구현할 수도 있지만,
And this sorry, I cannot answer
could be done via regex but very
하지만 이런 방식은 거의 사용하지 않습니다.
확장성이 없기 때문이죠.
rarely because
it's not scalable.
그래서 실제로는 이런 특성을 모델 자체에 포함시키기도 합니다.
And people actually embed this
property as part of the model.
사용자 쿼리가 적절하지 않다고 판단되면
이를 거부하도록 하는 기법들도 있습니다.
So you have techniques that
rejects user queries that
해로운 것으로 간주되는 경우죠.
are seen as harmful.
혹은 또 다른 현상으로
Or there is some
other phenomenon
hedging처럼 모델의 출력을 좀 더 완곡하게
만드는 것도 있습니다.
such as hedging that nuance
the output of the model
즉, 단정적인 답변을 피하기 위해서죠.
in order to not make
blanket statement as well.
이런 특징을 포함하는 데이터셋도 존재합니다.
So you might have data sets
that includes such flavors.
그리고 여러분이 다루는 작업에 따라
이 외에도 다양한 데이터셋이 있을 수 있습니다.
And you can have
many more depending
관심 있는 태스크에 따라 달라질 수 있습니다.
on the task of interest
that you're dealing with.
여기서 소개한 내용은
일반적으로 공개된 LLM들이
But what I'm listing here is
what usually the LLMs out there
범용 AI 비서 역할을 목표로 할 때
수집하는 데이터셋의 예시입니다.
that aim at being general
assistance gather.
보통 이런 범용적인 태스크에 대해
학습이 이루어집니다.
They tend to be like general
tasks that are being trained on.
데이터에 대해 질문 있나요?
Any questions on the data?
네.
Yep.
질문은 다음과 같습니다.
스토리 작성 예시에서
So the question is the
story writing example
어떤 종류의 시를
써야 하는지 명확하게 나타나 있지 않은데,
doesn't precise
what kind of poetry
이 스토리가 어떤 시에 대한 것인지
the story should be about.
애매할 수 있다는 점입니다.
So it might be ambiguous.
이런 경우 어떻게 일반화할 수 있을까요?
How can it generalize?
좋은 질문입니다.
So that is a great point.
이럴 때는 모델이 사전학습에서
얻은 지식에 의존하게 됩니다.
So we rely on the
model's knowledge
즉, 사전학습 단계에서
축적된 정보를 기반으로
that it has accumulated
at pre-training time
입력된 예시를 넘어
일반화할 수 있게 되는 겁니다.
to be able to generalize
beyond the examples
주어진 예시만 받아들이는 게 아니죠.
that it has been fed.
예를 들어, 이제 시에 관한
이야기를 만들어야 한다고 합시다.
So let's say, now, you
have a story about poetry,
사전학습을 통해 모델은
다양한 종류의 시에 대해 알고 있습니다.
and from pre-training, it
knows about all kinds of poetry
즉, 세상에 존재하는 여러 형태의 시를 인식하고 있죠.
that exist out there.
그래서 이런 예시를 학습한 후에는,
So you could imagine, after
fitting such an example at
지도 파인튜닝 단계에서는
이 프롬프트에 더 많은 세부 정보를 추가할 수 있습니다.
supervised fine tuning time,
that you could give more details
이 프롬프트에 세부 사항을 더 넣을 수 있다는 거죠.
to this prompt.
그러면 모델은
그에 맞춰서 이야기 생성도 일반화할 수 있게 됩니다.
And then the model
has the ability
이야기 생성 과정을
그 밖의 속성들을 반영해서 일반화할 수 있는 겁니다.
to generalize the generation
of the story with respect
즉, 추가적인 속성들에 맞춰 일반화가 가능한 거예요.
to those other attributes.
그래서 여러분이 예시로 들었던 것처럼--
So you can have--
방금 말씀하신 예시는
I think, the example
that you mentioned
LLM이 갖고 있는
놀라운 능력을 보여주는 좋은 사례입니다.
is a great example of the
magical ability of LLMs
즉, LLM이 자연어에 적응할 수 있다는 점이죠.
to adapt to natural language.
이 모든 것은 결국 모델이 과거에 봤던 데이터 분포와
우리가 모델에 가르치는 것에 달려 있습니다.
And all of that has to do
with the kind of distribution
과거에 어떤 분포를 봤는지, 그리고 우리가 무엇을 가르치는지가 중요합니다.
it has seen in the past
and what we teach it.
그래서 이야기 작성이라는 개념 자체가
모델의 핵심적인 학습 포인트가 되고, 이후에는 이를 일반화할 수 있게 됩니다.
So I think the concept
itself of writing stories
즉, 이야기를 쓰는 개념 자체가
모델이 일반화할 수 있는 핵심 학습이 되는 거죠.
is the key learning to the model
that it can then generalize.
이해되셨나요?
Does that make sense?
네.
Yeah.
좋습니다.
OK.
좋아요.
Great.
여기 또 다른 질문이 있었던 것 같습니다.
I think there was
another question here.
네.
Yeah.
질문은 alignment라는 용어에 관한 것이었습니다.
So the question is about
the term of alignment.
이게 바로 포스트 트레이닝 이후의 alignment를 의미하나요?
Is this post training what
is called as being aligned?
네, 저보다 한 발 앞서나가셨네요.
So you are ahead of me.
잠시 후에 슬라이드에서
그 내용을 다룰 예정입니다.
In a few slides, we're
going to talk about it.
좋은 질문이었습니다.
Great questions.
다른 질문 있으신가요?
Any other question?
아주 좋습니다.
Awesome.
Afshin이 사전학습 파트에서 설명했듯이,
So and then just like Afshin did
it for the pre-training part,
저도 대략적인 규모에 대해 소개하겠습니다.
I'm going to give some
orders of magnitude.
Afshin이 언급했던 GPT-3, 그리고 Llama 3 논문에서
So the same GPT-3
and Llama 3 papers
몇몇 수치를 가져온 것인데,
that Afshin referred
some numbers from
이 논문들에서는 실제로 통계치를 공개하고 있지는 않습니다.
don't actually give
their statistics
특히 인스트럭션 튜닝 데이터에 대해서는 토큰 수 기준이 아니라
in terms of token numbers for
the instruction tuning side
예시 개수로만 수치를 제시하고 있습니다.
but actually in
number of examples.
예를 들어, GPT-3는 약 13,000개,
So you see you have about 13
K used GPT-3 and 10 million
Llama 3는 1,000만 개의 예시를 사용했습니다.
for Llama 3.
네, 그렇죠.
And OK.
이제 간단히 추산해보겠습니다.
So let's do some
quick estimation.
각 예시가 약 1,000 토큰이라고 가정해 봅시다.
Let's say each example
is about 1,000 tokens.
이 숫자에 예시 개수를 곱하면,
When you multiply that with
the number of examples,
SFT에 사용되는 데이터셋의 크기를 대략 알 수 있습니다.
you see that the size of
the data sets used for SFT
이 크기는 사전학습에 사용했던 데이터에 비해
is several orders of magnitude
lower than the one used
몇 자리수 정도 더 작은 수준입니다.
for pre-training.
여기서 여러분이 가져야 할 개념은,
So the mental model that
you need to have here
사전학습은 아주 방대한 데이터를 사용해서
is that pre-training
is a lot of data
언어의 일반적인 특성을 학습한다는 점입니다.
you want to learn about general
characteristics, about language.
SFT는 그에 비해 조금 더 구체적인 작업에 맞춘다는 점이고요.
And then SFT is
more exactly what--
아까 누가 언급해줬듯이,
so someone was
mentioning just now
모델의 목표를 주어진 작업에 맞게 맞추는 것과 관련이 있습니다.
regarding alignments-- was
aligning the goal of the model
즉, 사용자가 원하는 작업에 적합하도록 모델을 맞추는 과정이죠.
to being suited for your tasks.
그래서 일반적으로 아주 고품질의 데이터셋을 사용하고,
So typically, very
high quality data
그 수량도 훨씬 더 적고, 정제되어 있습니다.
sets and much more concise and
precise in terms of number.
즉, 규모 면에서 훨씬 적은 수준입니다.
So less order of magnitude.
네, 좋습니다.
OK.
좋아요.
Great.
이제 다시 한번 연습문제를 풀어보겠습니다.
So now, let's try
this exercise again.
이번에는 우리 인스트럭션 튜닝 모델이 동일한 질문에 대해
What do you think could be the
answer to our instruction tuned
어떤 답변을 할지 한번 생각해보세요.
now model to the same question?
누구 답해보고 싶은 분 있나요?
Anyone wants to take a guess?
다시 시도해보시겠어요?
You want to try again.
네, 좋습니다.
Yeah.
정답은 '예'였습니다.
So the answer was yes.
곰인형을 세탁기에 넣을 수는 있습니다.
You can put in the teddy
bear in the washer,
하지만 곰인형은 세탁기에 넣지 않는 것이 좋습니다.
except that you shouldn't put
your teddy bear in the washer.
손세탁을 권장합니다.
You should handwash it.
이처럼 모델은 사용자에게 도움이 되는 답변을 제공합니다.
So it will give you the answer
that is helpful to the user.
이번에는 실제로 사용자 질의에 제대로 응답했습니다.
And indeed, this time
respond to the query.
꽤 괜찮은 결과라고 할 수 있습니다.
So which is pretty nice.
자, 이제 감독 파인튜닝의 장점에 대해
모두 살펴봤습니다.
So now, we talked
about all the things
이제 감독 파인튜닝의
좋은 점들을 정리해봤죠.
that are great about
supervised fine tuning.
이제 무엇이 어려움을 줄 수 있는지,
Now, I'm going to detail
a bit more about what
어떤 점이 도전적으로 만들 수 있는지
could make it hard
or challenging
좀 더 자세히 설명하고,
이후에 다룰 최적화 부분으로 연결하겠습니다.
and then motivate the
optimization part that we're
이 최적화 부분은 잠시 후에 다룰 예정입니다.
going to see afterwards.
우선, 앞서 간단히 언급했지만,
So first, we talked
about it a bit.
이런 데이터셋이나
When we have these
data sets, these data
SFT 학습을 위한 데이터 혼합물을 사용할 때는
고품질 데이터가 필요합니다.
mixtures for SFT training,
we need high quality data.
여기서 고품질 데이터란
And when you say
high quality data,
대개 사람의 개입이 포함된 데이터를 의미합니다.
means oftentimes human
involved in the loop,
모든 규칙과
you need to make sure it abides
with all the rules and all
사용자가 신경 쓰는 특성을 지키고 있는지 확인해야 하죠.
the characteristics that
the user will care about.
그래서 일반적으로 사람의 참여가 아주 큽니다.
So typically, it's
highly involved.
원래는 초기 모델들이
거의 전적으로 사람이 직접 만들었습니다.
So originally,
these first models,
초기 모델들은 사람이 전부 데이터를 만들었죠.
they were almost all human.
하지만 지금은 사람과 생성 데이터를
섞어서 사용하는 경우도 있습니다.
But now, you might have some
mixture of human and generation.
이런 방식의 장점 중 하나는
But one good thing
about these things
학습에 사용된 데이터셋을 반복적으로
is that the data sets they
are trained on are reused.
재활용할 수 있다는 점입니다.
So it's a work that you do
once, and you can complement
한 번 작업을 해두면, 이후에 추가로
with respect to time.
보완하거나 시간에 따라 확장할 수 있습니다.
But it's still very expensive
in time and resources.
하지만 여전히 시간과 자원이 많이 드는 작업입니다.
So the second point I want to
mention comes back to a point
누군가가 방금 SFT 데이터셋 분포와 관련해서 언급한 것과 관련이 있습니다.
that someone just made regarding
the distribution of your SFT
SFT 데이터셋의 분포가 실제 추론 시 분포와 어떻게 일치하는지에 관한 내용입니다.
data sets and how it would
align with actual inference
실제 추론 분포와의 관계죠.
distribution.
예를 들어 특정 종류의 시와 관련된 이야기를 예로 들어보겠습니다.
So in the case of
the story regarding
특정 종류의 시에 대한 프롬프트 분포를 생각해보면,
a specific kind of
poetry, the distribution
정확히 그 시 종류에 맞는 프롬프트 분포라면,
of prompts, that precise
the kind of poetry
일반화가 잘 일어날 수 있을 만큼 충분히 근접하다고 볼 수 있습니다.
seems close enough for
generalization to be made.
하지만 분포가 크게 다른 사례들도 생각해볼 수 있습니다.
But you could think about
examples that widely differ.
예를 들어, 영화 줄거리에 나오는 이야기를 요청한다고 해봅시다.
So let's say you ask for a story
that is in some movie plots,
그러면 교과서에서 볼 수 있는 이야기와는 다를 수 있습니다.
and it differs from the stories
that you might see in textbooks.
이렇게 되면 분포에서 약간 벗어난 사례가 될 수 있습니다.
So this could be slightly
out of distribution,
이 경우에는 일반화가 잘 안 될 수도 있습니다.
and it could have trouble
generalizing to that.
그래서 프롬프트 분포가 매우 중요합니다.
So prompt distribution
is very important.
그리고 프롬프트 분포를 목표 과업에 맞게 잘 맞추는 것이 중요하죠.
And aligning that prompt
distribution with respect
과업에 맞게 프롬프트 분포가 일치하도록 설계하는 것이 관심사입니다.
to the target task
is of interest.
네, 맞습니다.
Yep.
네, 그렇죠.
Yeah.
좋은 지적입니다.
Great point.
여기서 질문은 이런 것입니다.
So the question is
about, let's say,
SFT로 모델을 튜닝한 다음,
학습 데이터의 입력을 다시 모델에 넣으면
you have SFT tuned your model,
and now, you put a training
모델이 같은 이야기를 뽑아낼까요?
input back to the model.
정말 똑같은 이야기가 나올까요?
Will you get the same story?
이것은 아프신이 언급한 '암기' 현상과 관련이 있습니다.
So it has to do
with the phenomenon
아프신이 말했던 암기 현상과 연관된 내용입니다.
that Afshin was mentioning
regarding memorization.
실제로는, 대부분 같은 이야기가 나오지 않습니다.
So in practice, you will not
see the same story most likely
이는 샘플링을 할 때
because the sampling
that you're doing
제로(0)가 아닌 temperature를 사용하기 때문이죠.
is with a non ZeRO temperature.
전체적인 느낌은 비슷할 수 있지만, 단어 하나하나까지 똑같이 나오지는 않습니다.
It will maybe have the same
flavor but not word for word.
그 이야기의 전체 분위기는,
Then the flavor of
that story, if you
정확히 같은 프롬프트를 주면 비슷하게 나올 수 있습니다.
have the exact same
prompts, might be the same.
이것은 모델이 사전학습 때 어떤 데이터를 보았는지에 따라 달라집니다.
It depends on what it has
seen at pre-training time.
네, 그래서 만약에 제가
But yeah, so the
answer is that if I
그 구체적인 예시에 대해 예측을 해야 한다면,
had to give a guess on
that precise example,
아마도 비슷한 분위기는 날 수 있지만,
똑같은 단어로 나오지는 않을 겁니다.
it might be the same flavor but
definitely not the same wording.
맞아요.
Yeah.
또 샘플링이 다른 방향으로 이루어지면
전혀 다른 이야기가 생성될 수도 있습니다.
So and it might be
a different story
샘플링이 공간의 다른 영역을 지나가면
이야기가 달라질 수도 있습니다.
if the sampling goes through
some other region of the space.
이야기는 매우 창의적일 수 있고,
Stories are highly creative
and pre-training corpora
사전학습 데이터에는 여러 종류의 이야기들이 포함되어 있습니다.
of data mixture had all
kinds of stories in there.
그래서 특정한 이야기 예시는
So the specific
example of story is
매번 다른 결과를 생성할 가능성이 높습니다.
likely to generate
different outcomes.
네.
Yep.
질문은, 모델이 얼마만큼 다양한 출력을 내는지가
So the question is, will how
much the model wanders around
temperature 파라미터에 달려 있는지에 관한 것이었죠.
depend on the
temperature parameter?
네, 맞습니다.
And yes.
일반적으로 temperature 값을 높이면
So typically, when you have a
higher temperature, you also--
더 창의적이라고도 합니다.
so it's also called
more creative.
바로 그런 이유 때문이죠.
And it's for that reason.
또想하지 못했던 결과들도 생성될 수 있습니다.
It might also
generate things that
모델이 학습한 것에 비해 출력 확률분포에서
are less likely in its output
distribution with respect
확률이 더 낮은 것들도 나올 수 있습니다.
to what it has learned.
이런 점이 바로 우리가 배우는 사례와 같습니다.
And this is exactly a case
of something that we learn.
따라서 답은 '네'입니다.
So the answer is yes.
그리고 질문은, 그 부분을 조정할 방법이 있는가였습니다.
So the question is, is
there any way to tune that?
temperature를 조정하면 바로 그 효과를 볼 수 있습니다.
So when you tune
the temperature,
temperature를 조정하는 것이 정확히 그 작업이죠.
you exactly do that.
혹시 다른 방법을 생각하신 건가요?
Or were you thinking
about something else?
네.
Yeah.
또 다른 질문은, 혹시
So the question is, is
there something else
응답의 다양성을 얻을 수 있는
다른 방법이 있는지에 관한 것이었죠.
you could do to have
variations in the response?
이 부분에 대해 저는 간단하지만 어려운 해법이 있다고 생각합니다.
So for that, I have a
simple but hard solution.
해당 범주에 속하는 더 많은 데이터를
확보해야 합니다.
You will need more data
in that category that
이렇게 하면 모델이 어떤 확률분포를
타겟팅해야 하는지 이해할 수 있습니다.
will ground the model into
seeing what kind of distribution
이런 쿼리에 대해 우리가 원하는 분포를
모델이 파악하게 됩니다.
we target with such queries.
저는 이게 모델이 더 일반화하도록 도와줄 수 있다고 생각합니다.
And I think that will
be one way for the model
즉, 모델의 일반화 능력이 높아진다는 거죠.
to generalize more.
결국 데이터 측면에서 접근하는 것이 효과적일 겁니다.
So I think it will be
working on the data part.
다른 질문 있으신가요?
Was there another question?
네, 다 괜찮습니다.
All good.
네, 맞습니다.
So yeah.
이 질문은 정말 중요한데요,
So this is a very
relevant question
일반화라는 주제와 직접적으로 연관되어 있습니다.
because it touches on the
topic of generalization.
네, 그렇습니다.
So yeah.
데이터 혼합이 정말 중요합니다.
So data mixture matters a lot.
그리고 분포 공간 안에서,
충분히 드문 포인트를 확보하는 것이
And having points
that are sparse enough
모델이 무엇을 학습해야 하는지
파악하는 데 도움이 됩니다.
in the distribution
space to give
똑같은 예시를 반복하는 것이 아니라,
핵심적인 내용을 모델에 전달하는 것이죠.
the gist to the model of
what it needs to learn,
계속해서 같은 이야기를 반복하기보다는,
다양한 예시가 더 중요합니다.
rather than repeating the
same story again and again,
이 부분이 모델의 일반화 성능과 크게 관련이 있습니다.
will have a lot to do with
generalization powers.
그리고 이것은 곧 우리가 살펴볼 내용이기도 합니다.
And then this is something we
are going to see in a second,
우리가 이런 모델을 어떻게 평가할 수 있을지 볼 예정입니다.
how do you evaluate such models?
사용자로서 느끼는 모델의 유용함은
굉장히 주관적일 수 있습니다.
The feeling that you get
as a user on how helpful
그래서 이런 부분에 어떤 수치를 부여할 수 있는지가
중요한 주제가 됩니다.
a model tends to be subjective.
즉, 어떻게 수치적으로 평가할지에 대한 논의가
핵심이 되겠죠.
So how can you put some
number on it is going
이런 부분이 앞으로 다뤄질 주요 주제입니다.
to be a key topic of interest.
그리고 매우 가까운 시일 내에,
우리가 또 살펴볼 내용이 있습니다.
And then also very
soon, we're going
계산 비용을 어떻게 줄일 수 있을지도
곧 다루겠습니다.
to see how to make the
computations not that expensive.
Afshin이 학습 최적화 기법에 대해 이야기했었죠.
So Afshin talked about training
optimization techniques.
이번에는 파인튜닝 단계에서
한 번 더 나아가서,
But now, when we're at
the fine tuning stage,
우리가 어떤 단순화 가정을 할 수 있는지
살펴보겠습니다.
maybe we can go one
step further and see
어떤 단순화 가정을 적용할 수 있을지
함께 살펴보겠습니다.
what simplification
assumption we could make.
좋습니다.
OK.
아주 좋네요.
Awesome.
이제 이러한 도전 과제 중 하나인
평가에 대해 들어가 보겠습니다.
Now, let's dive into
one of these challenges,
여기서 언급할 부분이 바로 평가입니다.
which was the evaluation part.
사람들은 자신이 중요하게 생각하는 기준을
여러 범주로 나눠서 살펴봅니다.
So people have decomposed what
they care about in categories.
그래서 여기에는 평가에 사용되는
여러 가지 차원이 나와 있습니다.
So I'm listing here
some dimensions
이러한 차원에서 평가가 이루어지고,
that are evaluated
against and that
그 결과 어떤 정량적인 수치가 도출됩니다.
gives some quantitative number.
일반적으로 많이 사용되는
언어 벤치마크가 있습니다.
So you have a general
language where
이런 벤치마크에서는 보통 하나의 점수가
많이 사용되고 있습니다.
this benchmark that is
popular is generally one score
모두가 그 점수를 보고하죠.
that people reports.
그게 바로 MMLU, 즉 대규모 멀티태스크
It's a MMLU, which
massive multitask
언어 이해(Massive Multitask Language Understanding)입니다.
language understanding.
여기에는 약 50개 정도의
태스크가 포함되어 있습니다.
So it has, I think, 50
or so tasks in there
이 각각의 태스크에 대해
모델의 성능을 평가하게 됩니다.
where the model is
being evaluated against,
그리고 이렇게 얻은 점수를
다른 모델과 비교할 수 있습니다.
and you have some score
that you can compare with.
추론이나 수학적 추론 능력,
코드 생성에 대한 벤치마크도 있습니다.
You have benchmarks
on reasoning,
이처럼 수학적 추론이나 코드 생성 등
다양한 부문별 평가가 진행됩니다.
on math reasoning, as
well as code generation.
이 과정에서 수많은 약어들이 등장하고,
So here, you have all
sorts of acronyms,
실제로는 더 많은 벤치마크가 존재합니다.
and there is even way more.
즉, 벤치마크를 만드는 것 자체가
또 하나의 연구 분야가 되었습니다.
So basically, the
setting up benchmark
새로운 벤치마크가 끊임없이 등장하는 이유입니다.
has been one area of research.
연구자들이 기존 벤치마크에 성능을 맞추려 하면서
매번 더 많은 벤치마크가 제시됩니다.
So you always see more
and more benchmark
그리고 기존 벤치마크로는 평가가 어려운 영역을
새로운 벤치마크가 보완하게 됩니다.
coming in because people tend to
optimize for those that exist.
그러다 보면 평가의 공백이 생기기도 하고,
And then there are
some gaps that might
그 부분은 앞으로 더 많은 벤치마크가 채워줄 수도 있습니다.
be filled by further ones.
그리고 GSM 8K는
graduate school을 의미합니다.
And the GSM 8K stands
for grad school--
즉, 대학원 수준의 수학 문제라는 뜻이죠.
so yeah, grad school math.
8K는 예제의 개수를 의미합니다.
8K stands for the
number of examples.
네, 맞는 것 같습니다.
Yeah, I think so.
아니면 G가 다른 의미일 수도 있는데,
Or maybe G stands
for something else,
사실상 고등학교 수준 주제입니다.
but it's high school
topics basically.
그리고 많은 사람들이 흥미롭게 생각하는 패턴이 있습니다.
And one very interesting
pattern that people
이런 모델들이 등장하고 나서,
have seen as these
models came out
이 벤치마크로 평가를 해보면,
and as they were evaluated
against these benchmarks
같은 종류의 모델임에도 불구하고,
is that sometimes for
the same kind of model,
어느 순간 갑자기 성능 수치가 확 뛰는 경우가 있습니다.
you see all of a sudden a
spike in numbers with respect
어떤 벤치마크에서 이런 현상이 나타나는데,
to some of these benchmarks
without a clear explanation
명확한 설명이 없는 경우가 있습니다.
behind it.
여기서 제가 꼭 추천하고 싶은 논문이 하나 있습니다.
And there is this
paper that I highly
이 논문에서는 이런 현상을 자세히 살펴봅니다.
recommend taking a
look, which explores
여기서 주목하는 건 테스트 셋이 아니라, 테스트 작업 자체에 대해 학습하는 현상입니다.
the phenomenon of training on
the test task, not the test set.
테스트 작업이 중요한 겁니다.
The test task.
예를 들어, 수학적 추론을 다루는 벤치마크의 경우,
So when you have benchmarks
regarding math reasoning,
모델이 해당 유형의 데이터로
let's say, it matters
a lot if the model has
학습되었는지 여부가 상당히 중요합니다.
been trained on a
data that relates
즉, 그런 추론 데이터로 학습됐는지 아니면 아닌지에 따라 달라집니다.
to that kind of
reasoning versus not.
그래서 이런 벤치마크를 찾다 보면,
And this is why when you type
in those kinds of benchmarks,
모델이 추가로 학습에 쓸 수 있는 보조 훈련 세트가 있는 것을 볼 수 있습니다.
you will see that there are sets
of so-called auxiliary training
이런 데이터셋은 모델이
that can be used
for the model to be
같은 도메인에서 학습할 수 있게 해줍니다.
trained on the same domain.
이러한 방법으로,
And in that way,
it enables the fact
특정 능력에 대해 모델들을 비교할 수 있게 됩니다.
of comparing models with respect
to that specific capability.
이 논문에서 말하고자 하는 핵심은,
So what the paper
tries to convey here
모델끼리 비교하고 싶다면,
is that if you want to compare
models between each other,
각각 모델이 학습에 사용한 데이터 혼합을 비교해야 하고,
you need to compare the training
mixture it has been trained on
각 모델이 테스트 작업에 대해 학습했는지 여부도 맞춰줘야 한다는 점입니다.
and then ensure parity in terms
of training on the test task.
예를 들어 두 모델이
So you need to make sure that,
for example, the two have
테스트 작업에 대해 둘 다 학습했는지, 아니면 둘 다 학습하지 않았는지 확인해야 합니다.
been trained on the
test task or not.
만약 한 모델만 테스트 태스크로 학습되고
다른 모델은 그렇지 않다면,
And if it's one
and the other not,
이런 경우 두 모델을 비교하는 건
적절하지 않을 수 있습니다.
then it might not be a
good thing to compare them.
이렇게 하면 모델의 고유한 가치가
드러나지 않습니다.
It doesn't give you the
intrinsic value of the model.
그래서 이런 현상이
여기서 흥미로운 부분입니다.
So yeah, that's an
interesting phenomenon here.
질문 있나요?
Any questions?
알겠습니다.
OK.
좋습니다.
Great.
그럼 계속 진행하겠습니다.
So we can move on.
여기서 제가 말씀드리고 싶은 건,
So one thing that I
was mentioning here
모델이 얼마나 좋은지 파악하는 게
정말 어렵다는 점입니다.
is that it's very hard to
get a sense of how good
벤치마크 점수를 기준으로 해도
정확히 알기 힘듭니다.
a model is, even with
respect to benchmark scores,
왜냐하면 종종 발생하는 일이 뭐냐면,
because oftentimes what happens
is that as they come out,
연구자들이 학습 데이터에
벤치마크와 유사한 데이터를 설계하게 됩니다.
people design data
on the training site
그래서 우리가 벤치마크에서 풀고자 하는 것과
더 유사한 학습 데이터가 생기는 거죠.
that resembles more what we try
to solve on the benchmark side.
이렇게 하면 모든 분야에서
성능이 좋은 모델이 나오지만,
So sometimes you end up
with models that score great
사용자인 여러분 입장에서는
꼭 그만큼의 가치를 느끼지 못할 수도 있습니다.
everywhere, but you as
a user don't necessarily
실제 사용자가 체감하는
가치가 다를 수 있다는 의미입니다.
see added value to it.
이것은 모델의 잘못도 아니고,
And it's not the
fault of models.
벤치마크 자체의 문제도 아닙니다.
It's not the fault
of the benchmarks.
단지, 숫자 하나로 모델의 가치를
명확히 전달하는 것이 매우 어렵다는 거죠.
It's just that it's very hard
to give a number that conveys
즉, 모델이 여러분에게 어떤 가치를 주는지
숫자로 표현하기 쉽지 않습니다.
the value to you of the model.
그래서 이런 이유로 사람들이
다른 평가 방식들을 고안하게 된 겁니다.
So this is why people have
come up with other techniques
모델 평가에 숫자를 매기기 위한
다양한 방법이 나온 거죠.
to put a number on
model evaluation.
여러분도 Chatbots Arena라는 걸
들어보셨을 수 있습니다.
And you might have
heard of Chatbots Arena.
혹시 여기서 들어보신 분 계신가요?
Have any folks heard of it here?
네.
Yeah.
이 사이트는 모델을 제출할 수 있고,
So it's a website where
models can be submitted,
사용자들이 들어와 질문을 하면,
and users come in, and
they ask their questions,
두 모델의 답변이
함께 제시됩니다.
and they're presented
responses from two models.
그리고 어떤 답변이 더 나은지
사용자에게 평가를 받는 방식입니다.
And they're being asked to
judge which one is better.
그리고 웹사이트에서 일부 쌍별 비교 연산을 진행하고,
And then with some pairwise
computations done on the website
마지막에는 해당 비교 결과를 바탕으로,
각 모델을 어떤 순위로 정할지 랭킹이 결정됩니다.
side, they come up with some
ranking in the end that ranks
즉, 이 랭킹은 소위 '사용자 선호도'에 기반해
모델을 순위 매기는 방식이죠.
model with respect to, quote
unquote, "user preference."
결국 사용자들이 느낀 분위기를 수치로 나타낸 것이라 볼 수 있습니다.
So it's a number
that is being put
바로 사용자가 모델을 사용하며 느낀 인상에 점수를 매긴 셈이죠.
on the vibes seen by the user.
그럼 이 방식이 완벽할까요?
And is it all perfect?
사실, 그렇지 않습니다.
Actually, no.
여러 가지 한계점이 존재하는데요,
So it suffers from
several issues that are--
특히 다루기 어려운 또 다른 문제들이 있습니다.
another set of issues that
are hard to deal with.
예를 들어, 새로운 모델이 추가될 때마다
So among them, when you have
a new model that comes in,
초기 비교 과정에서 잡음이 발생할 수 있습니다.
you have some noise at
the beginning with respect
이때 어떤 모델과 비교하느냐에 따라
to which other model it's
being compared against.
이 초기 단계가 랭킹 결과에 상당히 큰 영향을 미치고,
And these first few steps
actually influence quite a bit
이 때문에 전체 랭킹이 쉽게 바뀌는 취약한 성질이 생깁니다.
the actual ranking, which
makes it a brittle property.
관련해서 실제로 이런
And there is a
paper that actually
리더보드를 쉽게 조작할 수 있다는 논문도 있습니다.
shows that it's easily possible
to rig such a leaderboard.
그래서 실제로 그렇게 조작된 사례가 있는지는
So I'm not sure if there
is any evidence that it
확실하지 않지만,
has been done in the past.
어떤 모델이든 사용할 수 있어서,
But you can use
any model, if you
예를 들어 '너는 누구야?'라고 물어보면
ask the question,
who are you, it's
모델이 자신이 누구인지 대답하게 됩니다.
just going to say who it is.
예를 들어, ChatGPT에게 '너는 누구야?'라고 묻는 경우입니다.
If you ask ChatGPT, who are you.
그러면 '저는 ChatGPT입니다,'
It's going to say,
hey, I'm ChatGPT,
'저는 여러분을 도와주는 어시스턴트입니다.'라고 답하죠.
I'm a helpful assistant.
이 논문에서는 이런 아주 단순한 특성을 활용해
And this paper observed on
this very simple property
평가 대상 모델이 무엇인지
that it was able to
detect what model
식별할 수 있다는 점을 지적했습니다.
was being evaluated against.
만약 악의적인 사용자가 있다면,
And let's say, you have
an adversarial player,
맞는 모델을 골라내서 랭킹을 조작할 수도 있는 겁니다.
it could rig the ranking just
by selecting the right model.
즉, 이 방식이 완전히 안전하다고 할 수는 없습니다.
So it's not foolproof.
그리고 또 다른 측면에서는,
And then on other
aspects, so some
이런 모델들을 평가하는 벤치마크 중에는,
of the benchmarks that
evaluate these models,
실제로 전문가들이 엄선해서 만든 경우가 있습니다.
they're actually
curated by experts
이 전문가들은 주어진 프롬프트가
어떤 결과를 내야 하는지 그 타깃 분포를 잘 이해하고 있죠.
that know very well about the
target distribution of what
즉, 특정 프롬프트에 대해 기대되는 정답이 무엇인지 아는 겁니다.
a given prompt should give.
그래서 이런 벤치마크에는 명확한 가이드라인이 있어서
이게 사실인지 아닌지를 구분할 수 있습니다.
So it has a set of guidelines
that says clearly, OK, this
이건 사실이다,
is factual.
이건 사실이 아니다,
This is non-factual.
이런 식으로 좋은 답변과 나쁜 답변을
구분할 수 있게 합니다.
So they're able to determine
what is good versus bad.
하지만 여러분이 사용자라면
이런 정보를 모를 수 있습니다.
And you as a user, you
might not know about it.
예를 들어, 테디베어 관련 예시를 생각해 봅시다.
Because let's just take the
example of the teddy bear
여러분이 테디베어를 세탁기에 넣고 싶다고 할 때,
that you wanted to
put in the washer,
테디베어를 손빨래해야 한다는 걸 모른다면,
if I don't know that I need
to hand wash my teddy bear,
그리고 세탁과 관련해 자세한 답변을 받았다면,
and if I have a detailed
response regarding
예를 들어, 찬물로 세탁기에 돌리라는 답변을 받을 수 있죠.
you need to wash it with
a machine wash cold,
사용자인 저는 이런 조언이 실질적으로 도움이 된다고
느낄 수 있습니다.
and I could, as a user,
find these pieces of advice
실제로 행동으로 옮길 수 있으니까요.
helpful because they
are actionable to me.
하지만 이런 답변이 정말 사실일까요?
But actually, are they factual?
이건 사실 사용자 입장에서는
또 다른 문제입니다.
That is a whole other set
of issues that you as a user
실제로 많은 질문에서
여러분이 사실 여부를 판단하기 어렵습니다.
wouldn't be able to tell
on a lot of queries.
그리고 우리가 직면하는 또 다른 문제는
사용자 취향입니다.
And another challenge that we
have here is a user preference.
여기서 LLM 답변에 이모지가 들어가는 걸 좋아하는 분 계신가요?
So who here likes it when there
are emojis in LLM responses?
네?
Yes?
아니요?
No?
네.
Yeah.
저는 개인적으로 이모지가 들어가는 걸 좋아합니다.
Personally, I do.
그리고 이 부분에 대해 의견이 정말 분분하죠.
And I think there
are strong opinions.
이모지를 전혀 좋아하지 않는 분들도 있습니다.
And some people
don't like it at all.
그래서 그런 답변은 점수를 낮게 줄 수 있죠.
So they will down
rank such responses.
사실 이런 건 사용자가 직접 판단하고 선택해야 하는 문제입니다.
But actually, it's something
that the user should
사용자가 직접 구분하고 선택할 수 있어야 합니다.
be able to tell and choose.
그리고 사람들의 분포가
And then the
distribution of people
최고의 모델을 선택하는 사람들의 분포가
who choose the best
model with respect
이 모델을 실제로 사용할
더 넓은 인구 집단의 분포와
to the distribution of
the wider population that
차이가 날 수 있습니다.
is going to use
these models is going
이런 분포가 종종 다르게 나타납니다.
to be different oftentimes.
이모지 사례가 좋은 예라고 생각하는데요,
And I think the emoji
case is a good example,
일반적으로 이모지는
because I think
generally, emojis
더 넓은 대중 사이에서 인기가 많죠.
are popular in the
wider population.
하지만 도메인 전문가들은 이모지를 그리 선호하지 않을 수 있습니다.
But I think domain experts
might not like it as much.
그래서 이런 불일치를 여기서 볼 수 있다고 생각합니다.
So I think that mismatch is
one that you would see here.
그리고 마지막으로 언급하고 싶은 것은 안전성 측면입니다.
And then the last one I will
mention here is the safety side.
사용자 입장에서는,
So you as a user,
you don't really
모델이 본인의 프롬프트를 거부하는 상황을
그다지 좋아하지 않죠.
like it when a model
rejects your prompts.
무언가를 물었을 때 모델이 '죄송합니다, 답변할 수 없습니다.'라고 하면
When you ask about something,
and it says, OK, hey, sorry,
사실 그렇게 답하면 사용자로서는 별로 반갑지 않습니다.
I cannot answer it.
그래서 실제로 답변을 제공하는 응답 쪽으로
바이어스가 생기게 됩니다.
So there will be a bias towards
responses that actually respond
즉, 어떤 안전 원칙을 지키는 것보다
사용자의 질문에 응답하는 쪽으로 치우치게 되죠.
to your query, rather than
respect some safety principle
결국에는 이게 제품적으로 의도된 결정일 수도 있습니다.
that might be eventually the
intended product decision.
이처럼 여기에도 이런 종류의 바이어스가 나타납니다.
So there is also this kind
of bias that pops up here.
그리고 아까 말씀드렸듯이,
모델 평가라는 게 쉽지 않은 과제입니다.
And as I was mentioning,
evaluation is a hard problem.
여러 가지 관점에서 살펴볼 수 있죠.
So you have all these
angles that you can explore.
하나의 점수만으로는
여러분이 신경 쓰는 모든 것을 알 수 없습니다.
And it's not one number
that's going to tell you
여러 요소들이 결합되어야 합니다.
what you care about.
이 모든 요소들의 조합이 중요합니다.
It's the combination
of all of these.
결국 여러분이 실제로 필요한 것에 맞게 맞춰져야 합니다.
And in the end, it's tailored
to what you actually need.
따라서 주어진 모델의 장점과 단점을 파악하고
So you would need to see
the strengths and weaknesses
어떤 모델이 자신의 쓰임새에
가장 잘 맞는지 결정해야 합니다.
of a given model and to
determine which one corresponds
즉, 본인의 활용 사례에 맞는 모델을 선택해야 합니다.
to your use case.
마지막으로 다시 한 번 얼라인먼트 질문으로 돌아가 보겠습니다.
So I'm going to come back to one
question about alignment here.
다음 강의에서는 한 단계 더 나아가서
So we're going to see at the
next lecture a further step
모델이 여러분이 원하는 일을 수행하도록
into aligning the
model to do what
정렬하는 방식, 즉 preference tuning이라는 과정을
you want to do in a step
called preference tuning.
그리고 파인튜닝과 preference tuning을
And then the combination of fine
tuning and preference tuning,
사전학습 후에 이어지는 이 두 단계를
which comes after
pre-training, is what
모델의 정렬(alignment)이라고 부릅니다.
we call alignment of the model.
이렇게 두 단계를 모두 alignment라고 합니다.
So these two steps
are called alignments.
그리고 한 가지 더 언급하고 싶은 내용이 있습니다.
And I want to call
out one other thing.
여기서 아직 이야기하지 않은 단계가 하나 더 있습니다.
There is one step we
didn't mention here
최근에 등장한 단계인데, ‘mid training’이라고 불립니다.
that is called mid training
that has been emerging
이 단계는 사전학습 직후에
very recently, which
consists in a step
데이터의 종류를 정렬하는 과정에 해당합니다.
just after pre-training in
aligning the kind of data
즉, 모델이 학습하는 데이터의 종류를
that the model is being
trained on to the tasks
여러분이 실제로 원하는 태스크에 맞게 맞추는 것입니다.
that you really care about.
사전학습의 목표는 같지만,
So it's the same
pre-training objective
태스크와 데이터셋을 여러분이 원하는 방향으로 정렬하는 과정입니다.
but aligning the kind of tasks
and the kind of data sets
다시 말해, 여러분이 신경 쓰는 주제에 맞추게 되는 거죠.
to something that
you care about.
이처럼 mid training은 최근에 등장한 흐름입니다.
And yeah, so it's
an emerging trend.
아직 설명을 하진 않았지만, 여러분이 참고로 알아두시라고 말씀드렸습니다.
I have not mentioned it,
but just so that you know,
mid training은 사전학습과 파인튜닝 사이에
mid training is
something that you
위치하는 단계라고 보시면 됩니다.
would have between
pre-training and fine tuning.
다 이해되셨죠?
All good?
네, 좋습니다.
OK.
아주 좋습니다.
Great.
이제 파인튜닝과 관련된 도전과제 중에서
So now, we're going to tackle
one aspect of the challenges
저희가 언급한 문제, 즉
that we had mentioned
regarding fine tuning, which
계산 자원 소모가 크다는 점에 대해
is computational expense--
살펴보겠습니다.
the fact of being
computationally expensive.
그리고 그 문제를 해결하기 위한 대표적인 기법 중 하나인
And we're going to look at it
with one well-known technique
LoRA라는 방법에 대해 알아보겠습니다.
called LoRA, which
is a technique
파인튜닝 단계에서 가중치를 효율적으로 파인튜닝하는
to fine tune your weights
at the fine tuning stage
효율적인 방법입니다.
in an efficient manner.
그래서 이 기법은 널리 사용되고 있습니다.
So it's widely used.
그리고 계산 자원을 크게 절약해줍니다.
And it saves a lot of compute.
가중치 행렬을 살펴보면,
So when you look at
your weight matrices,
전체 가중치 행렬을 직접 파인튜닝하는 대신,
instead of directly fine
tuning the whole weight matrix,
LoRA 기법은 파인튜닝을 분해해서
the LoRA technique
decomposes the fine tuning
사전학습된 모델의 가중치와
between the weights of
the pre-trained model
추가적인 가중치로 나눕니다. 이 추가 가중치는
and additional weights that
it decomposes into a low rank
저랭크 행렬 곱셈 형태로 분해됩니다.
multiplication.
이 방식에서는 사전학습된 가중치가
So in this formulation,
the pre-trained weights
고정(frozen)되어 있습니다.
that you have is frozen.
여기서 W0는 고정된 값입니다.
So this W0 is frozen.
그리고 B와 A는 새롭게 조정해야 하는 행렬들입니다.
And then B and A are the
matrices that you need to tune.
B와 A는 일반적으로
So B and A are typically--
각각 전체 행과 전체 열의
so they have dimensions that
will match the number of rows
차원을 맞춰서 구성됩니다.
and number of
columns respectively
즉, B의 행 수와 A의 열 수는
for the number of rows of B
and number of columns of A.
각각 원래 행렬과 같고, B의 열과 A의 행 차원은
But then the dimension of the
columns of B and then rows of A
R이 됩니다. 이 R은 랭크(rank)로,
is R, which is the rank of these
matrices, which is typically
보통 아주 작은 값으로 정해집니다.
taken very small.
원래 W의 차원은 수백이나 수천인 경우가 많지만,
So the dimensions of W is
typically hundreds or thousands,
R의 차원은 대략 10 정도로 매우 작습니다.
and the dimension of R is
typically up to 10 or O of 10.
그래서 전체적으로 보면 학습해야 할 가중치 수가
So as you can imagine, it
results in much less weights
훨씬 줄어듭니다.
to train.
그리고 여기에 추가적으로
And then I will mention
just other techniques
효율성을 높이고 파인튜닝을 좀 더 쉽게 하기 위한
to improve efficiency and
then ease the fine tuning,
프리픽스 튜닝(prefix tuning), 어댑터(adapter) 같은 기술도 있습니다.
some methods called a
prefix tuning and adapters.
이런 방법들은 교재에 설명되어 있으니,
So they're explained
in the class textbook.
여기서는 자세하게 다루지는 않겠습니다.
But we're not going to dive
deep into them because they're
이 방법들은 실제로는 덜 자주 사용됩니다.
less commonly used.
하지만 여러분이 이런 방법들도 있다는 건 알아두시기 바랍니다.
But just so that you know.
이제 LoRA가 실제로 어떻게 동작하는지 자세히 살펴보겠습니다.
So let's walk through in
detail how does LoRA work.
여러분이 모델을 파인튜닝하고 싶을 때,
So when you want to
fine tune your model,
이미 사전학습된 여러 가지 가중치가 있겠죠.
so you have all
these ways for which
이 가중치들로 확률분포를 이미 학습해둔 상태입니다.
you have already
learned a distribution
이건 사전학습 단계에서 학습된 분포입니다.
at pre-training time.
파인튜닝을 수행하는 가장 단순한 방법은
So one naive way of
operating fine tuning
이 기존 가중치들을 직접 업데이트하는 것입니다.
would be to directly
iterate on these weights.
하지만 여기서 우리가 하는 방식은,
But what we're doing
here, as we said,
이 가중치를 기존에 학습한 가중치와
is to decompose these into the
weights that we have already
행렬 곱의 형태로 분해해서 사용하는 것입니다.
pre-trained on and this
product of matrices.
LoRA의 핵심 아이디어는
이 두 가지 항 모두에 대해 포워드 패스를 한 뒤,
And what LoRA says is that
you can do a forward pass
최종적으로 이 값들을 합쳐준다는 점입니다.
on both these
terms and then adds
즉, 끝에서 이 양들을 더해주는 방식이죠.
these quantities in the end.
여기서 행렬 A와 B는 여러분이 관심 있는 과업을
And A and B is going to
be a characterization
특정짓는 특징이 됩니다.
of your task of interest.
예를 들어 여러분이 어떤 모델을 가지고 있다고 가정해봅시다.
So let's say you
have a model that--
Afshin이 예로 들었던 것처럼
so Afshin was mentioning
the kinds of tasks
모델을 특정한 태스크에 맞게 특화할 수도 있습니다.
that you can maybe specialize
your model on, for example,
예를 들어 스팸 탐지 같은 작업이 있습니다.
spam detection.
먼저 여러분이 사전학습된 모델을 사용하고,
So you would take your
pre-trained model,
여기서 B와 A라는 행렬을 가중치에 도입한 뒤,
instantiate this B
and A in weights,
그 가중치를 가지고 파인튜닝을 진행합니다.
in the weights of your
model, fine tune on them.
그렇게 하면 최종적으로 B와 A는
And then what you will
have is that B and A
이 스팸 탐지 태스크에 특화된 형태가 됩니다.
are going to be specific to
this task of spam detection,
감정 분석과 같은 다른 태스크에도 같은 방식으로 적용할 수 있습니다.
similarly for sentiment
extraction and so on.
즉, 이런 방식의 장점은
So it's a very nice
property that you
기본 모델에서 시작해서 가중치를 추가로 조정할 수 있다는 점이고,
can start from a base model,
further tune your weights,
A와 B가 각각의 태스크에 맞춰 특화된 형태로 남는다는 것입니다.
and then have your A's and
B's that are task specific.
이제 어디에서 이 행렬들이 학습되는지 이야기해보겠습니다.
So I want to comment
now on where were
이 LoRA 행렬들이 어디에서 학습되는지에 대한 설명입니다.
these matrices being learned.
LoRA의 원 논문에서,
So in the original
paper of LoRA,
어텐션 행렬에만 학습을 적용한다고 언급되어 있습니다.
it mentioned training only
on the attention matrices.
하지만 나중에는 사람들이 이런 방식이
But later on, people
realized that it might not
성능 향상에 가장 효과적인 위치가
be the place where
it has the most
아닐 수 있다는 것을 알게 되었습니다.
positive impact on performance.
그리고 몇 주 전에 나온 한 블로그에서
And then there is a blog
that came out a few weeks ago
이 부분을 자세히 분석했는데, 그 결과
that studies this into
detail, and then they
실제로 피드포워드 블록이
realized that the feed-forward
blocks are actually
LoRA를 적용했을 때 가장 효과적인 부분이라는 것을 확인했습니다.
those where putting
LoRA is most beneficial.
그래서 요즘은 두 컴포넌트 모두 LoRA 행렬을 갖지만,
So today, typically, both these
components carry LoRA matrices,
실제로 성능 향상은 대부분
but the bulk of the
performance improvements
피드포워드 블록에서 발생합니다.
is actually contained in
the feed-forward block.
그리고 LoRA에 대해 흥미로운 특성 두 가지를 말씀드리겠습니다.
And then I want to mention
two interesting properties
첫 번째는 LoRA에 관한 내용입니다.
about LoRA.
LoRA 가중치로 파인튜닝할 때는
So when you fine tune
with LoRA weights,
더 큰 러닝레이트를 사용하는 것이 좋습니다.
you want to use a
higher learning rate.
보통 기존보다 10배 더 크게 잡는 것이 권장됩니다.
So typically, 10 times
more is the guidance.
그리고 재미있는 점 중 하나는,
And then one interesting
fact is that it
배치 사이즈를 크게 하면 성능이 잘 나오지 않는다는 것입니다.
doesn't perform as well when you
train it with larger batch size.
각 방법에 대해 좋은 이론적 설명을
So I don't have a good
theoretical explanation
드릴 수는 없습니다.
to give you for each of them.
이것들은 주로 실험적으로 관찰된 결과입니다.
It's more empirical observations
that have been emitted.
하지만 이 현상을 연구하는 사람들이 공유하는
But to give the main lines
behind the mindset shared
주요 관점을 간단히 소개하면,
from people who study
this phenomenon,
첫 번째로는, LoRA 행렬의 랭크가 작을 수 있기 때문에
the first one might be guided
by the rank of the LoRA matrices
이 부분이 원인이 될 수 있습니다.
that might be small.
그래서 탐색해야 할 공간이 넓기 때문에,
And as a result, given
the regions of space
더 높은 러닝레이트가 필요하게 됩니다.
that it needs to explore, you
need a higher learning rate.
두 번째 가설은
And then the second
one, the hypothesis
여기에서, 행렬 곱의 학습 동역학이
here is that the training
dynamic of products of matrices
완전한 행렬의 경우와는 다르다는 것입니다.
is different than a full matrix.
그리고 바로 이 부분에서
배치 사이즈가 증가하는 현상이 나타납니다.
And this is where the increasing
batch size phenomenon occurs.
즉, 이런 설명들이
So it's basically
the explanations,
현재까지 제시된 가설적 설명입니다.
tentative explanations
given there.
이제 이 부분의 최적화 방법을 살펴보겠습니다.
So now, we're going to explore
an optimization of this.
하지만 본격적으로 들어가기 전에,
But before I dive
deep into that part,
LoRA 부분에 대해 질문 있는 분 계신가요?
does anyone have any
questions on the LoRA part?
네.
Yep.
좋은 질문입니다.
Great point.
질문은, 랭크에 대해 그리드 서치를 하느냐는 것이네요.
So the question is, do you
do grid search on the rank?
네, 할 수도 있습니다.
So you could.
보통 랭크 R은 설계 선택입니다.
So it's a design choice
to rank R. Typically,
대부분의 경우, 이미 다른 사람들이 실험을 해봤기 때문에
people would have
done it before you.
적절한 랭크가 어떤 값일지 감이 잡힙니다.
So you have an idea of what
rank could be well suited
그래서 자신의 용도에 맞는 값을 고를 수 있죠.
for your use case.
물론 그리드 서치를 해볼 수도 있고,
So you could definitely
do grid search,
아니면 그냥 널리 쓰이는 값을 택할 수도 있습니다.
or you could just
pick a popular value.
예를 들어 4라는 값이 자주 사용됩니다.
I think a 4 is used commonly.
그래서 그 중 하나를 그냥 사용해도 됩니다.
You can just go
with one of them.
네.
Yeah.
그리고 우리는 매개변수 수가
이미 상당히 많이 줄어든다는 점을 볼 수 있습니다.
And we are going to see
that the reduction in number
이미 파라미터 개수가 엄청나게 줄어들기 때문에,
of parameters is so huge
already that reducing even more
거기서 더 줄이는 것은 그다지 중요하지 않을 수도 있습니다.
maybe doesn't matter that much.
초반에 오더 단위로 줄이는 것만으로도 큰 효과가 있습니다.
That initial reduction by orders
of magnitude goes a long way,
그리고 그 부분은 결국 하이퍼파라미터 튜닝에 해당합니다.
and that is just a
hyperparameter tuning.
어떤 세팅에서 랭크를 얼마로 두느냐는
And you can see a
given rank in a given
설계 선택의 하나라고 볼 수 있습니다.
setup as being a design choice.
이제 2분이 남았으니
빠르게 정리해보겠습니다.
So we have two
minutes, and we're
이제 퀀타이즈드 LoRA에 대해
간략히 살펴보겠습니다.
going to quickly
cover quantized LoRA.
방금 Afshin이 언급한
기술들을 보면,
So the techniques
that Afshin mentioned
바로 가중치 퀀타이즈를 통한
방법이 있었죠.
just now regarding
quantizing weights
즉, 메모리 사용량을
줄이는 것인데요.
and so reducing the
memory footprint
이제 여기서 그 내용을
직접 확인해보겠습니다.
is something that we're
going to see just here.
여기 W0, A, B와 같은
행렬을 보면,
So when you look at these
matrices W0 and A and B,
이 논문에서 사람들이 한 일은
what people have
done in this paper
W0의 가중치를 아주 스마트한
포맷으로 퀀타이즈하는 것입니다.
is to quantize the weights of W0
into a format that is very smart
그리고 그 후에 이 행렬들에 대해
계산 및 반복 작업을 진행합니다.
and then compute and
iterate on these matrices
여기서 학습되는 행렬인 A와 B는
풀 프리시전 즉, BF16으로 계산됩니다.
that are being learned, A and
B in full precision, which
여기서는 BF16으로 표현되는 거죠.
is in that case BF16.
그리고 이렇게 얼려진(frozen)
가중치들의 퀀타이즈 방법이
And then the quantization
of these frozen weights
굉장히 똑똑하게 설계되어 있습니다.
is super smart.
NF4라는 포맷을 사용하는데,
It's in a format
called NF4, which
이 포맷에서는 가중치가 정규분포를
이룬다고 가정합니다.
assumes that the weights
are distributed normally.
그리고 고정된 크기의 버킷이 아니라
분포를 여러 분위수로 나눕니다.
And it splits the space into
quantiles rather than buckets
이렇게 하면 각 구간에 들어가는
값의 개수가 비슷해지죠.
of fixed size, which puts
about the same amount of number
즉, 각 분위수마다 값이
비슷하게 배분됩니다.
of values into each.
그래서 인코딩에 사용하는 비트가
효율적으로 최적화됩니다.
So it optimizes the bits
that you use for encoding.
또 이 방식에서는 이중 퀀타이즈
과정을 거칩니다.
And what it does is that it does
a double quantization process.
먼저 가중치를 퀀타이즈하고,
So it quantizes the weights.
그리고 두 번째 단계에서는
And then in a second
step, it quantizes
이제 여기서 자세히 다루지는 못했지만
퀀타이즈 상수들도 퀀타이즈합니다.
the quantization constants that
we didn't see at length here.
전체 가중치를 퀀타이즈 상태와
풀 프리시전 상태로 변환할 때,
But basically, when you want
to convert your full weights in
이 과정에서 생성되는 상수들이
and out of quantized
states, you have
바로 그런 상수들입니다.
constants that are generated.
그리고 논문에서는 이 상수들까지
퀀타이즈하자고 제안합니다.
And they propose to quantize
these constants as well.
이 방법을 적용하면
16배 VRAM 절감 효과를 가져왔고,
So this method generated
minus 16X VRAM savings,
이중 퀀타이즈 방식까지 하면
추가적인 절감이 더 생깁니다.
and then the double quantization
methods gave some extra savings
하지만 그렇게 큰 추가 절감 효과는 없었습니다.
but not that much.
그래도 이런 시도가 있다는 점은 흥미롭습니다.
But it's interesting to know.
그리고 이제 정확하게 시간이 다 되었습니다.
And then we are exactly on time.
오늘도 들어주셔서 감사합니다.
Thank you for your time.